<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Prodromos the fore-runner of Christ's peaceable kingdom upon earth.</title>
            <author>Sherwin, William, 1607-1687?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59939</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3409</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34233</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14153354</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14153354</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102121</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59939)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102121)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1070:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Prodromos the fore-runner of Christ's peaceable kingdom upon earth.</title>
                  <author>Sherwin, William, 1607-1687?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Sherwin.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Revelation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Second Advent.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102121:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102121:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ΠΡΟΔΡΟΜΟΣ: THE FORE-RUNNER OF CHRIST's Peaceable KINGDOM upon EARTH.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Mal. 4.5.</hi>
                  </bibl> Behold I will ſend you <hi>Elijah</hi> the Prophet, before the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the great and dreadful Day of the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Matth. 17.11.</hi>
                  </bibl> Jeſus anſwered and ſaid unto them, <hi>Elias</hi> truly ſhall firſt come, and reſtore all things: but I ſay unto you, <hi>Elias</hi> is come already, and they knew him not, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Evening and the Morning were the firſt Day: <hi>ſo of the 2d, 3d, 4th, 5th, and 6th dayes,</hi> Gen. <hi>1.5, 8, 13, 19, 23, 31.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Likewiſe will the dark Evening precede the ſeventh Millenary of the World: in reference whereunto note the words of St.</hi> Peter,
<bibl>
                     <hi>2 Pet. 3.8.</hi>
                  </bibl> A thouſand years as one day.</p>
               <p>Poſt funeſtam <hi>Gogi</hi> &amp; <hi>Magogi</hi> cladem, <hi>(i.e.</hi> Papae &amp; Turcae)
<bibl>
                     <hi>Ezek. 38.39.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Deſcribitur <hi>Nova Hieruſalem</hi> cui nomen <hi>[Jenovah Shamma]</hi> Dominus. Ibid. c. <hi>48.</hi> ad finem.</p>
            </q>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Baptiſtes Dominum, Meſſiam praeit</hi> Elias,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aurorum Vesper, funebria tetra triumphum.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Baptiſt did the Lord precede:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Elias</hi> Moſhahh will:</l>
               <l>The Night, the Day: Chriſt's triumph ſhall</l>
               <l>The Earth with ſlaughter fill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hoc Omega ſuis</hi> Munus, <hi>&amp; Alpha tulit.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Chriſt this for his did bring; ſo <hi>Munus</hi> for his friends.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1665.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:102121:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>True Chriſtian Friend, whoever thou art or maiſt be,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>AS</hi> in the ſequel both of this little Parcel, and of the therein-named Tract of <hi>Chriſt's Kingdom on Earth to come,</hi> I have endeavoured with the Woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> to impart to thee, and all that truly fear God, as good news for thy whole ſpirit, ſoul and body, as I have received from Chriſt; and am perſwaded in my own heart that I have been taught chiefly and remarkably from his Word and Spirit: Yet ſith that there are (I conceive by the ſame means) ſetled apprehenſions wrought upon my heart, of terrible things to come upon the World before that time; If ſuch admonition thereof may be uſeful unto thee, or ſuch Warning made profitable to any perſons that hereafter God may (in mercy) bring out of the <hi>Myſtical Babylon,</hi> or any other bondage of Satan, before the great enſuing Deſtruction come, and ſo by this or any ſuch means, thou mayeſt receive benefit to thy ſoul, or promote it to others: and that I may ſelf may at leaſt be clean from the blood of all men (as the Apoſtle ſpake to thoſe refractory <hi>Jews,</hi> his Brethren according to the fleſh, <hi>Acts 18.6.)</hi> I have (under the Glory of the great God, and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, ſhortly to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, as <hi>Tit. 2.13.)</hi> attained my end herein. And for what remains, I ſhall not ceaſe to pray in the behalf of thee and others, that by the Bleſſing of God upon this poor endeavour, or any other good means, which he may in his good pleaſure raiſe up to ſuch bleſſed purpoſes: that ſo from all of us, to his moſt holy and glorious Majesty the due praiſe of all his glorious Grace may evermore be rendred through Jeſus Chriſt, and by the Lord the Spirit. In whom I am and ever ſhall be thine, in all he hath, or may hereafter make me uſeful to ſerve thy ſoul as ſuch.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>MUNUS.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Septemb. 29. 1664.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="biblical_prophecy">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:102121:2"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. Or, <hi>A Warning to the wicked World. A Watch-word to wiſe Virgins</hi> Rev. 14.4.</head>
            <head type="sub">Dan. 12.10. <hi>None of the Wicked ſhall underſtand. — But the Wiſe ſhall underſtand.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="Scriptural_passages">
               <head>
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.1.</head>
               <p>BEhold, the Day cometh that ſhall burn as an Oven, and all the proud, yea, and all that do wickedly ſhall be as ſtubble; and the Day that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſhall burn them up, ſaith the LORD of Hoſts, that it ſhall leave them neither root nor branch.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3. Behold, I will ſend my Meſſenger <hi>[to wit, to the Jews]</hi> and he ſhall prepare the way before me: and the LORD, whom ye ſeek, ſhall ſuddenly come to his Temple; even the Meſſenger of the Covenant, whom ye delight in: Behold, he ſhall come, ſaith the LORD of Hoſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 2. But who may abide the Day of his coming? and who ſhall ſtand when he appeareth? for he is like a Refiners fire, and like Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers ſoap.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 3. And he ſhall ſit as a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finer and Purifier of Silver: and he ſhall purifie the ſons of Levi, and purge them as Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, that they may offer unto the LORD an Offering in Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:102121:3"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 19.27. But thoſe mine Enemies, which would not that I ſhould reign over them, bring hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſlay them before me: <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>(2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.8.) The Wicked-one <hi>[with his followers]</hi> whom he ſhall deſtroy with the appearance of his coming.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. — There ſhall be a time of trouble, ſuch as never was ſince there was a Nation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 24.23. Alas, who ſhall live when God ſhall do this?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Scriptural_passages">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:102121:2"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.15.</head>
               <p>BEhold, I come as a Thief. Bleſſed is he that watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and keepeth his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, leſt he walk naked, and they ſee his ſhame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Haggi</hi> 2.6, 7. Thus ſaith the LORD of Hoſts, Yet once it is a little while, and I will ſhake the Heavens and the Earth, and the Sea, and the dry Land.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 7. And I will ſhake all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the Deſire of all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhall come. <hi>With</hi> Heb. 12.26.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.2, 3. But unto you that fear my Name ſhall the Sunne of Righteouſneſs ariſe with healing in his wings, and ye ſhall go forth, and grow up as calves of the ſtall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 3. And ye ſhall tread down the wicked; for they ſhall be aſhes under the ſoals of your feet, in the day that I ſhall do this, ſaith the LORD of Hoſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17, 18. And they ſhall be mine, ſaith the LORD of Hoſts; in that day that I make up my Jewels, and I will ſpare them as a man ſpareth his own ſon that ſerveth him.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:102121:3"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 18. Then ſhall ye return, and diſcern between the righteous and the wicked; between him that ſerveth God, and him that ſerveth him not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.4, 5. Theſe are they which were not defiled with Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, <hi>[avoiding the Idolatry of the times]</hi> for they are Virgins
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as a chaſt Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin unto Chriſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. <hi>They reject Image and Idol-worſhip: Worſhip of evil men departed, and Saints, of Croſſes and Crucifixes, Opinion of merit, works of Supererogation, Church-Treaſury, Saints Interceſſion, Mens Pardons, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, and all ſuch devices, for freeing them from their ſins: as alſo all opinions of Self-ſufficiency, Free-will, Light within them, Natural-conſcience, Creature-ſufficiency, or any thing that intrencheth upon any of Chriſts Offices, as their Prophet, Prieſt or King, who is all to them for Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs, Sanctification and Redemption,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.30.</note>: theſe are they which follow the Lamb whitherſoever he goeth: theſe were redeemed from among men, being the firſt fruits unto God, and to the Lamb.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 5. And in their mouth was found no guile: for they are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fault before the Throne of God.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="biblical_prophecy">
            <head>Certain ſuitable and ſeaſonable portions of Prophetical-Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, left for the benefit of Wiſdoms Children, here ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to be obſerved by them in order following.</head>
            <p>THe firſt is, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.12. <hi>And the ſixth Angel poured out his Vial upon the great River</hi> Euphrates, <hi>and the water thereof was dryed up, that the way of the Kings of the Eaſt might be prepared.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 13. <hi>And I ſaw three unclean Spirits, like Frogs, come out of the mouth of the Dragon, and out of the mouth of the falſe-Prophet.</hi> [Which three unclean Spirits (according to <hi>Paraeus</hi>) may be firſt thoſe <hi>Legati a Latere,</hi> or <hi>Plenipotentiaries,</hi> ſent to Princes. 2dly. Popiſh Biſhops and Doctors. 3dly. Prieſts, Jeſuites, &amp;c. by a joynt miſſion, 1. from the Devil, the old Dragon by inſtigation. 2dly. From the Popes Council of Cardinals, and their Aſſociats by advice. And 3dly, from the Beaſt himſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> the Pope by his authorized Commiſſion.]</p>
            <p>Ver. 14. <hi>For they are the Spirits of Devils, working Miracles, which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102121:3"/>go forth unto the Kings of the Earth, and of the whole World, to gather them to the Battel of the great Day of God Almighty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 15. <hi>Behold, I come as a Thief. Bleſſed is he that watcheth, and keepeth his garments, lest he walk naked, and they ſee his ſhame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 16. <hi>And he gathered them into a place, called in the Hebrew tongue,</hi> Armageddon.</p>
            <p>Ver. 17. <hi>And the ſeventh Angel poured out his Vial into the Air, and there came a great Voice out of the Temple in Heaven, from the Throne, ſaying, It is done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 18. <hi>And there were Voices, and Thunders, and Lightnings: and there was a great Earthquake, ſuch as was not ſince men were upon the Earth, ſo mighty an Earthquake, and ſo great.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 19. <hi>And the great City was divided into three parts, and the Cities of the Nations fell: and great</hi> Babylon <hi>came in remembrance before God, to give unto her the Cup of the Wine of the fierceneſs of his Wrath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 20. <hi>And every Iſland fled away, and the Mountains were not found.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 21. <hi>And there fell upon men a great Hail out of Heaven, every ſtone about the weight of a talent: and men blasphemed God, becauſe of the plague of the Hail: for the plague thereof was exceeding great.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That probably this Prophecy hath already begun to take place: ſee further in the ſecond Letter, dated the 20th of <hi>May</hi> 1664. But the latter part of the former Prophecy ſeems again to be decyphered (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Mr. <hi>Mede</hi>) <hi>Revel.</hi> 14.14. to the end; which he conceives may be fulfilled in the utter ruine both of <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Turk,</hi> by an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate hand of Chriſt, at his coming with his glorious Angels, at the beginning of the <hi>Thouſand years,</hi> Rev. 20. Which great Deſtruction is ſet forth by two reſemblances of the ripe Harveſt of the Earth, and the ripe Cluſters of Grapes of the Vine of the Earth: [by the firſt, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the ripe Harveſt of the Earth, he underſtands the <hi>Turk</hi> with his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents, in <hi>ver.</hi> 14, 15, 16. as follows,</p>
            <p>Rev. 14.14. <hi>And I looked, and behold a white Cloud, and upon the Cloud one ſate like the Son of man:</hi> [which deſcription, he obſerves, alwayes in the Scripture belongs to Chriſt] <hi>having on his head a Golden Crown, and in his hand a ſharp Sickle.</hi> Vide <hi>Joel</hi> 2.13.</p>
            <p>Ver. 15. <hi>And another Angel came out of the Temple, crying with a loud Voice to him that ſat upon the Cloud: Thruſt in thy Sickle and reap, for the time is come for thee to reap, for the Harveſt of the Earth is ripe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 16. <hi>And he that ſate on the Cloud, thruſt in his Sickle on the Earth, and the arth was reaped.</hi> This he underſtands of the <hi>Turks</hi> ruine: then follows the <hi>Popes,</hi> under the reſemblance of the ripe cluſters of Grapes, of the Vine of the Earth, <hi>ver.</hi> 17, 18, 19, 20.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:102121:4"/>
            <p> Ver. 17. <hi>And another Angel came out of the Temple which is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, he alſo having a ſharp ſickle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 18. <hi>And another Angel came out from the Altar, which had power over fire, and cryed with a loud cry to him that had the ſharp ſickle, ſaying, Thruſt in thy ſharp ſickle, and gather the cluſters of the Vine of the Earth, for her grapes are fully ripe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 19. <hi>And the Angel thruſt in his ſickle into the Earth, and gathered the Vine of the Earth, and caſt it into the great wine-preſs of the wrath of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 20. <hi>And the wine-preſs was trodden without the City, and blood came out of the wine-preſs, even unto the horſe bridles, by the ſpace of a thouſand and ſix hundred furlongs.</hi> Thus of the <hi>Pope</hi> and his Adherents likewiſe (though that laſt deſtruction is like to be of both <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Pope</hi> at once) as making up in both the whole myſtical Antichriſt,
<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Homes.</hi>
               </note> as another learned man conceives, when they are gathered unto the <hi>Armageddon</hi>-Battel at the great day of God Almighty, as before, Chap. 16. for they may both be ſaid to ſit in the Temple of God; the <hi>Turk</hi> holding the Land in his poſſeſſion where the material Temple of God formerly ſtood, keeping out the <hi>Jews,</hi> which ſhall be converted, and poſſeſs it, and yet holds in part the Old Teſtament and Circumciſion, though groſly perverting both: the other, namely the <hi>Pope,</hi> ſitteth where the myſtical Temple ſhould be glorious, but he hides the glory of it, and ſets up himſelf there as if he was God, being as it were, the one Eye, one Arm, and one Leg, making up one half of the myſtical Antichriſt, as the <hi>Turk</hi> doth the other, according to the ſaid learned Authors illuſtration. Or further, ſaith Mr. <hi>Mede,</hi> The <hi>Harveſt</hi> may denote the deſtruction of the great City, and the <hi>Vintage of the ripe Grapes of the Earth</hi> may ſet forth the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Kingdom of the Beaſt ſoon after to follow; even as the Vintage followeth ſpeedily after the Harveſt, which ſeems to be moſt probable, and ſuitable to <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>But a third myſtical Prophecie, as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> again obſerves, ſeems more fully to ſet out this laſt deſtruction of Antichriſt in the utmoſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, as follows <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11. to the end of the Chapter; which is ſet down after that excellent deſcription of the Jews Converſion, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 66.8. [when that Nation will be born in a day] <hi>Ver.</hi> 7. when there will be ſuch joy and gladneſs, that that Bride eſpecially hath made her ſelf ready for the marriage of the Lamb, (yet probably with other Gentiles likewiſe) and after thoſe many Hallelujah's both for that and the deſtruction of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> firſt by much people, <hi>verſ.</hi> 1, 2, 3. then ſecondly, by the four and twenty Elders, and thirdly by the great multitude, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. but in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth verſe follows the exceeding joy for the great Grace beſtowed upon Gods <hi>Iſrael,</hi> (with other Gentiles coming in at that time) ſaying, <hi>Let us
<pb facs="tcp:102121:4"/>be glad and rejoyce, and give honour to him, for the marriage of the Lamb is come, and his Wife hath made her ſelf ready,</hi> &amp;c. But after all theſe, <hi>ver.</hi> 11. begins a peculiar Viſion given to St. <hi>John,</hi> in what a glorious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Chriſt, the King of kings, and Lord of lords, would come to deſtroy thoſe great Enemies at that time, formerly mentioned, with an utter ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and irreſiſtable deſolation: <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11. <hi>And I ſaw Heaven opened, and behold a white horſe, and he that ſat upon him was called, Faithful and True; and in righteouſneſs he doth judge, and make war.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 12. <hi>His Eyes were as a flame of fire, and on his Head were many Crowns, and he had a Name written that no man knew but he himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 13. <hi>And he was clothed in a Veſture dipt in blood, and his Name is called, The Word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 14. <hi>And the Armies that were in heaven followed him upon white horſes, clothed in fine linnen, white and clean.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 15. <hi>And out of his mouth goeth a ſharp Sword, that with it he ſhould ſmite the Nations: and he ſhall rule them with a rod of Iron: and he treadeth the Wine-preſs of the fierceneſs and wrath of Almighty God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 16. <hi>And he hath on his Veſture and on his thigh a Name written, KING OF KINGS, AND LORD OF LORDS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 17. <hi>And I ſaw an Angel ſtanding in the Sun, and he cried with a loud voice, ſaying to all the fowls that fly in the midſt of Heaven, Come and gather your ſelves together unto the ſupper of the great God:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 18. <hi>That ye may eat the fleſh of kings, and the fleſh of captains, and the fleſh of mighty men, and the fleſh of horſes, and them that ſit on them, and the fleſh of all men both free and bond, both ſmall and great.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 19. <hi>And I ſaw the Beaſt, and the Kings of the earth, and their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, gathered together to make war againſt him that ſat on the horſe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Army.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 20. <hi>And the Beaſt was taken, and with him the falſe Prophet</hi> [hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily <hi>Mahometan,</hi> as well as <hi>Popiſh</hi>] however all Antichriſtian Enemies] <hi>that wrought miracles before him, with which he deceived them that had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the mark of the Beast, and them that worſhipped his image. Theſe both were caſt alive into a lake of fire burning with brimſtone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 21. <hi>And the remnant were ſlain with the Sword of him that ſat upon the horſe, which Sword proceeded out of his mouth: and all the fowls were fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with their fleſh.</hi> Thus largely is explained this conqueſt of Chriſt at the <hi>Armageddon</hi>-Battel, when his Enemies ſhall eminently be made his Footſtool, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.1.</p>
            <p>Thus having briefly touched on theſe three approaching Prophecies out of the [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] or little Book given to St. <hi>John</hi> to eat up, <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. we ſhall adde one contemporary with them out of the ſame Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102121:5"/>about the end of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, and the entrance of Chriſt's Viſible Dominion in the room and place thereof, and of all other, being a ſhort abridgment of the Seventh Trumpet, which there ends all time: Rev. 11.13. <hi>And the ſame hour there was a great Earthquake, and the tenth part of the City fell; and in the Earthquake were ſlain of men Seven thouſand</hi> [<hi>viz.</hi> Men of eminent name or note, though haply civilly] <hi>and the remnant were afrighted, and gave glory to the God of Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 14. <hi>The ſecond Wo is paſt, and behold, the he third Wo cometh quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 15. <hi>And the Seventh Angel ſounded, and there were great Voices in Heaven, ſaying, The Kingdoms of this World are become the Kingdoms of our Lord, and of his Chriſt, and he ſhall reign for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 16. <hi>And the twenty four Elders, which ſate before God on their ſeats, fell upon their faces and worſhipped God,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 17. <hi>Saying, We give thee thanks, O Lord God Almighty, which art, and waſt, and art to come: becauſe thou hast taken to thee thy Great Power, and haſt reigned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 18. <hi>And the Nations were angry, and thy Wrath is come, and the time of the Dead, that they ſhould be judged, and that thou ſhouldeſt give re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward unto thy Servants the Prophets, and to thy Saints, and them that fear thy Name ſmall and great, and ſhouldeſt deſtroy them that deſtroy the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 19. <hi>And the Temple of God was opened in Heaven, and there was ſeen in his Temple, the Ark of his Teſtament, and there were Lightnings, and Voices, and Thundrings, and an Earthquake, and great Hail.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as this laſt Prophecy (with all the former) ſpeaks terror to the enemies of God in theſe latter dayes; ſo, much comfort to his faithful People to enſue thereupon: as likewiſe did the fore-mentioned firſt part of the 19th Chapter. And therefore upon both conſiderations, let all ſuch as would approve themſelves in the number of wiſe Virgins, ſeriouſly conſider, and diligently enquire into the ſeries and order of theſe Prophetical Predictions, the better to diſcern the ſeaſonableneſs of the matter contained in them, that ſo they may be enabled to make a due improvement thereof, eſpecially by earneſt and faithful prayer, which is God's Peoples uſual prevailing means for obtaining both the removing of evils, and the enjoyment of good: as <hi>Daniel, David, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi> and others, have frequently by experience found. In reference whereunto there are part of two Letters, with other Papers here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ſubjoyned: The one containing ſome affecting previous appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions concerning the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> coming down out of Heaven from God, Chap. 21.10. The other containing ſome ſubſequent ſerious conſiderations in reference to the order of <hi>Revelation-Prophecies,</hi> and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102121:5"/>other things, the better to ſet home ſuch due conſideration and improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof; which are now ſo much the more neceſſary by how much the times of any of their accompliſhment may be near approaching: the one of the ſaid Letters preceding, the other occaſionally following a Tract intitled, <hi>[A peaceable Conſideration of Chriſts peaceful Kingdom upon Earth, in the thouſand Years,</hi> Rev. 20. <hi>under or after the ſeventh Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet:]</hi> Unto which are annexed certain <hi>Theſes</hi> or Poſitions agreeing to holy Scripture, and the Analogy of Faith, tending to make way for the Doctrine of the ſaid Kingdom of Chriſt: All being apt to be premiſed before the ſaid Tract.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="doctrine">
            <head>I ſhall here ſet down theſe <hi>Theſes</hi> or Poſitions agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Scriptures and Analogy of Faith, which hold out the Symmetry and fit proportion, ſuiting with the Doctrine of Chriſts Kingdom upon Earth, from the moſt general and eminent manifeſtation of Chriſts three great Offices, of Prophet, Prieſt, and King, in the three great Periods of the World; whence are drawn ſix Inferences to prove the Kingdom of Chriſt, in the Tract called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</head>
            <p>THe firſt thing we named to be done, was the laying down of thoſe <hi>Theſes</hi> or Poſitions agreeing to the holy Scripture, and the Analogy of Faith, that may make way for Doctrines of this nature: Which are theſe that follow:</p>
            <p>Firſt, That as the
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 11.7, 8, 9.</note> infinite excellencie of the Nature and Being of the Trin-Une-Deity
<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut</hi> 6.4. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.4, 6. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.16, 17. &amp; 28.19.</note> was everlaſtingly
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.3.</note> incomprehenſible in it ſelf, ſaving onely ſo far as the ſame Divine Eſſence hath been pleaſed to communicate any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of it ſelf by
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.13, 14, 15, 16. <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.6, 7.</note> Word, or
<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.1. &amp; 145.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20.</note> Works, or both, unto any Creatures in Heaven or Earth; ſo hath the Trinity of Perſons in the Unity of the Divine Eſſence, both in the Eternal Decrees, and in the execution of all
<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.6.</note> joyntly in their order concurred, and ſo
<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 5.17. with <hi>John</hi> 14.10, 11, 16.</note> will do from Eternity through all Times unto all Eternity.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that all the glory of God the Father was by the Eternal Decree to be manifeſt
<note n="h" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.3, 4, 5.</note> in Jeſus Chriſt his onely
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102121:6"/>begotten Son, the Lamb ſlain in the Eternal Decree of the Father
<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.8. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19, 20.</note> before the foundation of the world was laid: And according to the ſaid Eternal Decree, the holy Ghoſt
<note n="k" place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7.</note> one God co-eſſential and co-equal with the Father and the Son,
<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 15.26.</note> proceeds from the Father and the Son, the
<note n="m" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5.</note> Mediator between God and Man, as the ſole
<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.2. <hi>John</hi> 14.16, 17, 26.</note> efficacious Worker and Accompliſher of all ſpiritual good, in and for Angels and Men, &amp;
<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.17.</note> all real good in all Creatures, which in their ſeveral
<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.11.</note> Orders and Natures they were capable of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Accordingly in the Creation God made the
<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.27, 28, 29, 30.</note> World by his Wiſdom, the Eternal Word, <hi>John</hi> 1. the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſitting (as it were) upon the ſurface of the Waters then co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the Earth, powerfully to produce the Creatures then to be made, and ſo both the Heavens with the Angels (as Divines conceive) and the Earth, were made the firſt day, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.1. as all that were made in the whole World after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, in the five following days; which the word <hi>Elohim</hi> in the plural number, put with the Verb <hi>[Barah]</hi> in the ſingular number, denoting the Trinity of Perſons in the Unity of Eſſence, ſeems to declare; whoſe concurrence in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of man, is likewiſe very remarkably expreſt, when God ſaid, <hi>Let Us make Man after Our own Image, after Our likeneſs, Gen.</hi> 1.26.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The making of
<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.11.</note> Angels in Heaven, and Man, and all Creatures in the World, was in the execution of the ſaid incomprehenſibly glorious Trin-Une-Deity, in their ſeveral Orders, Natures, Stations, and Conditions.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, As no other but the holy and good Will and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the infinitely glorious and incomprehenſible GOD, was the reaſon and cauſe why they were all made abſolutely as they were; ſo that they ſhould be for Himſelf, as
<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.4.</note> his Word witneſſeth, as their utmoſt End, and no other incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent Reaſons or Ends ought to be given or aſſigned by men.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, As the
<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.31.</note> whole Creation was all good, ſuitable to the Author of it, ſo the preſerving, ordering, over-ruling and diſpoſing of all Creatures, according to his good Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, by his infinite Wiſdom, Power, Providence, and Goodneſs,
<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.33.</note> is not to be meaſured or judged by any ſcant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of any created Capacity; who will notwithſtanding be
<note n="w" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.4.</note> juſtified in his ſaying, and clear when he is judged;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102121:6"/>there being in ſuch his proceedings ſo many fathomleſs depths in reſpect of Creatures, which it is not lawful for any men to ſearch into, further then Gods Word doth warrant them; but in things not revealed, or forbidden,
<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.29.</note> they are not to enquire.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Since God according to his ſaid Eternal De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, and good pleaſure of his will, at the Fall of our firſt Parents in Paradiſe, revealed and teſtified his wonderful powerful Grace, That <hi>the bleſſed Seed of the Woman ſhould break the Serpents Head;</hi> there is ſufficient ground
<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 51.5.</note> for ever to humble all mankind, and
<note n="z" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10.</note> for ever to exalt Gods free and rich Grace therein; and
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, 12.</note> all men are thereby engaged to uſe all GOD's means to obtain their part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
            <p>Eightly, According to the Declaration of that wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful rich and free Grace of God, for the Salvation of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and for carrying on his great Deſign therein: As the Father Son, and holy Ghoſt, by an Eternal Decree had pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed ſo to be wonderfully glorified in the powerful Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption and Salvation of
<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28, 30, 33.</note> his elect People, in ſuch a way of free Grace; ſo in the creation of all things, all ſorts of Creatures were made
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 15.18.</note> in a capacity to carry on that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign; and from that very period of their firſt being, holily and moſt wiſely over-ruled and diſpoſed of
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.91.</note> in reference thereunto; and ſo ever ſince have been, are, and ſhall be moſt wonderfully, holily and powerfully (though many times ſecretly and unſearchably) throughout all Ages, by the joynt concurrence of all the ſaid three Perſons of the moſt ſacred Trinity, in their order of working,
<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.17. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. <hi>John</hi> 13.18.</note> to the infallible per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting and compleating of the ſaid Deſign, Decree, and Purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, That the
<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.2. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.20. <hi>John</hi> 3.16. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5.</note> mannagement and adminiſtration of the great work of Mediatorſhip between God and Man, ever ſince the ſaid promiſed Seed was revealed to our firſt Parents, hath been committed to Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God, who in his Word commands all men
<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.5 <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.35.</note> to hear him,
<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.12 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.6.</note> by acknowledging, receiving, and obeying him.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, That the mannagement and adminiſtration of Mediatorſhip between God and Man hath ever ſince been executed by Chriſt in his three great Offices, wherein He, and he onely is to appear moſt powerful, wonderful, gracious
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102121:7"/>and glorious to his Church upon Earth, as her great
<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 3.22.</note> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,
<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.5, 6.</note> Prieſt, and
<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.6.</note> King.</p>
            <p>Eleventhly, Chriſts execution of the ſaid three great Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, is two ways to be conſidered:</p>
            <p n="1">1. More generally, for his univerſal Church, in reſpect of the
<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.1. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15.</note> ſeveral ſeaſons wherein in order he was to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute them ſeverally moſt eminently, until his work of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atorſhip ſhould perfectly be accompliſhed, and
<note n="n" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.18 19, 20, 21.</note> full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation made between God, and all his elect People, his
<note n="o" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12, 27.</note> myſtical Body the true Church being compleat in all the Members of it, and perfect Union and Communion at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with himſelf as their Myſtical Head, together with the
<note n="p" place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.3.</note> Father, and the holy Spirit; as alſo with the glorious Angels, and one with another, in moſt happy enjoyment of all Good, to all Eternity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is again conſiderable, particularly and ſpecially in reſpect of every truly believing Soul, in the particular ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the efficacy of thoſe three great Offices to them by his holy Spirit, making good means and ordinances effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to every faithful Soul, ſo exhibiting himſelf to them,
<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 3.22.</note> as their great Prophet, inwardly, powerfully, and ſaving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, teaching them all neceſſary Truth and Doctrine: ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.15,</note> as their great High Prieſt, in the like way evidencing their Peace and Reconciliation with God, through that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piation that he ſhould or hath made for their ſins: thirdly, in the like way alſo to evidence to them at one time or other
<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 2.36.</note> that he is their powerful King and Protector, that hath, and doth, and will ſubdue all his and their Enemies, and keep them in a loyal and good condition, by Faith and Grace unto Salvation.</p>
            <p>Twelfthly, Conſider that the general, more eminent, and glorious execution of thoſe three great Offices for his uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church, more remarkably in the World, is in theſe three great Periods of his manifeſting himſelf in the World, according to all that his
<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.34.</note> Father had given him to do.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As
<note n="u" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.19 20.</note> the great Prophet of his Church, by his Spirit of Wiſdom and Revelation, in all his immediate Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, till his coming in the Fleſh; and ſo Chriſt is ſaid to preach in the time of <hi>Noah,</hi> to the Spirits in Priſon, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.19, 20.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As
<note n="w" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.4. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.6. &amp; 7. Chap.</note> the great high Prieſt, in the ſecond Period after
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102121:7"/>his coming in the fleſh, when putting an end to all the Types and Shadows of his Prieſthood, he actually undertook in his Perſon, and executed the Work and Office of Prieſthood, as the great High Prieſt, having made a full and perfect attonement and ſatisfaction for the ſins of all his People, he aſcended into the
<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.1.</note> Holy of holies, the higheſt Heavens, there ſitting at the right Hand of God the Father, powerful and glorious, there to execute and improve that Office, by making interceſſion for his People till his coming again.</p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15 <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.10.</note> In the third great Period of the World, under the ſeventh Trumpet, Chriſt will appear more eminently in executing the Office of a King in this general conſideration, in reſpect of his Univerſal Church, ſubduing wonderfully and manifeſtly in the world
<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.27. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11. <hi>to the end.</hi>
               </note> his own and his Churches Enemies powerfully
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.4, 5, 6.</note> graciouſly enabling his Saints to walk in the obedience of his Laws, taking away, in a great degree, the evils of ſin and ſuffering, with the cauſes of both, by
<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev. cap.</hi> 19, 20.</note> binding of Satan, and deſtroying the wicked powers of the World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſay in a great degree, though not then
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.7, 8, 9, 10.</note> totally nor finally.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Conſider how Chriſt hath and doth and will work in theſe three great Periods of the World; In the firſt he wrought by
<note n="d" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11, 12.</note> his Spirit of Wiſdom and Revelation, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king known the Will of the Father in all things for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, reſpecting Faith and Obedience; In the ſecond, By
<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.17. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.17.</note> his Spirit of Grace and Truth, powerfully ſanctifying his people more eminently and largely then in the former: In the laſt, When he will take to himſelf his Kingly Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15, <hi>&amp;</hi> 19. by
<note n="f" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.7.</note> his Spirit of Power and Domination.</p>
            <p>What things concern this third Period, ſee further after the large Paper, <hi>December</hi> 7. 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:102121:8"/>
            <head>Novemb. 3. 1663. <hi>Part of a Letter, ſent to a Friend, not long after the Writer thereof had more intenſively inquired into the laſt times, in order held out in the Book of the</hi> Revelation <hi>of Jeſus Christ, contained under the ſeventh Trumpet,</hi> Rev. 11.9 <hi>and Thouſand years of Chriſt's Reign on Earth,</hi> Rev. 20.</head>
            <p>AS for the <hi>New-Jeruſalem,</hi> ſince the bar was taken away, whereby I have formerly conceived it to be an Article of Faith, which the Scripture expreſly declared, <hi>viz.</hi> [That the Heavens muſt contain Chriſt's Perſon till his coming the ſecond time to Judgement] My meaning was, <hi>to the laſt Judgment.</hi> I have (I ſay) found much ſince in Scripture (but eſpecially in the Book of the <hi>Revelation</hi>) to tend to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt, as the great Monarch, to ſet up his glorious Kingdom, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the putting down all other worldly Powers that ſtood in oppoſition to him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. when he will begin to judge the quick and dead, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.17, 18. I have lately peruſed Mr. <hi>Archers</hi> Book of Chriſt's <hi>Perſonal Reign,</hi> and though in all things therein I am not ſatisfied, yet I cannot find ſolid reaſon in many things, to diſſent; and in other things it ſeemeth convincing; and doubtleſs in his time he was a very diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chriſtian, and I had of late, (before I read that, or any other of the like nature, ſince my moſt earneſt ſearch into myſtical Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the latter times) the ſame apprehenſions of divers paſſages in Scripture, which I find to agree with his Book: as the applying what our Saviour promiſed to his Diſciples when he came to his Kingdom, [which I find will be in the Thouſand years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. promiſed to the <hi>New-Jeruſalem</hi> Inhabitants, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21.] that then they ſhould ſit on twelve Thrones, judging the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And that of our Saviour, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.24. that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhould be trodden under foot till the times of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> be fulfilled, [but to be raiſed up again then.] And when he wept over <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> he ſaid, <hi>They</hi> (namely that People of the <hi>Jews) ſhould not ſee him thenceforth, till they ſaid, Bleſſed is he that cometh in the Name of the Lord,</hi> Mat. 23. <hi>ult.</hi> denoting that then they ſhould ſee him. And that Promiſe, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10. to the end, which is in a way of mercy, foreſhewing how upon their Converſion, they ſhould <hi>mourn</hi> in humble contrition, and <hi>look to him at his appearing</hi> [when that Nation ſhall be born in a day, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.8.] which judicious Expoſitors apply to the expreſſion, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Behold, he cometh with Clouds, and every eye ſhall ſee him; and they alſo that pierced him</hi> (that is, the People of the <hi>Jews,</hi> that after their imprecation on themſelves, and on their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102121:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>children, ſhall be accompliſhed) <hi>will</hi> (as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.) <hi>appear to be beloved for their Fathers ſake,</hi> when thoſe times of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.19. and then all <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be ſaved (both of <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile:</hi>) And though many grave Divines for a long time interpreted all that hath been ſpoken to this purpoſe, for the moſt part to a ſpiritual ſenſe, yet the things that ſome hold out to the contrary, ſeem eaſie to be anſwered: ſo that if this Opinion, or rather matter of Faith, be but freed from thoſe evil addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that the ſubtilty of Satan in the primitive times thruſt upon it (as if it ſhould be a Kingdom of <hi>ſenſual pleaſure;</hi>) for before this miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations, or falſe aſperſions rather, as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> notes, it was very antient. And freed likewiſe from that bold preſumption and ſcandalous wickedneſs of our latter times, for any, under pretence of <hi>Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> given to the Saints, to go about by the Sword, or any other unlawful means, to diveſt Magiſtrates and Governors of their Offices, to take that Kingdom before Chriſt give it to them to whom it will belong, as being appointed to them by his Father, in his own time, namely, at Chriſts ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing. [Here conſider that Chriſt ſaith, <hi>he came not to deſtroy the Law;</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>he eſtabliſhed the Law;</hi> and this is neceſſary to vindicate this Doctrine from ſcandal, and to warn well-meaning perſons that they think not upon ſeeming-fair pretences of good, to attempt to do evil; God having revealed, that he will ſet up that Kingdom himſelf, and that only in his own appointed time. On the other ſide, ſaith our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>He that breaketh the leaſt Commandment, and teacheth men ſo, ſhall be the leaſt</hi> (that is, none) <hi>in the Kingdom of Heaven</hi>] As he anſwered the mother of <hi>Zebedees</hi> children, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.23. <hi>It ſhall be given to them for whom it is appointed of my Father:</hi> appointed as well for the time <hi>when,</hi> as perſons <hi>to whom.</hi> Theſe and the like errors being removed from it, I think it may have an honourable and comfortable place in matter of true Chriſtian Faith, as containing the beſt times of the moſt holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church upon Earth, that we are to believe or hope for, and the excellenteſt Communion of Saints that we are in this world to expect. And likewiſe, that we are now ſpecially by our prayers to labour to promote (as God of old directed his People, when their time of deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from <hi>Babylon</hi> drewon, <hi>Jer.</hi> 39. <hi>Then</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>they ſhall call on me, and I will anſwer, &amp;c.</hi> And when <hi>Daniel</hi> by Books underſtood the mind of God, therein he ſet himſelf by faſting and prayer, to ſeek for, and help forward (if it might be) the accompliſhment of ſuch revealed Grace: So now alſo that <hi>new Babel</hi> is abundantly revealed to God's People, to be ſhortly to be thrown down, and the <hi>New-Jeruſalem,</hi> much more abundantly revealed in Scripture, ſhortly thereupon to be ſet up:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102121:9"/>The Faith and Prayer of God's People ought in their ſphear to ſeeks to promote it; and I obſerve the <hi>Dutch Notes</hi> (though by men of different Judgments) yet in the Preface of the nine laſt Chapters of <hi>Ezekiels</hi> Prophecy, apply what is there ſaid to ſome wonderful Glory of a <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> to come, of which the former reſtoring of the <hi>Jews</hi> from old <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> was but a Type: Beſides, I obſerve many Pſalms, and many paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in many other Pſalms more than I reade in Mr. <hi>Archers</hi> Book, to tend ſo this way, that otherwiſe (as ſuch Prophetical-Scriptures be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides) ſeem not to have any probable fulfilling [but according to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, Interpretation (as I may call it) which I muſt acknowledge I never did, nor ever was like rightly and groundedly to have underſtood, but according to the tenour of that bleſſed Book. And as <hi>Iſraels</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> tended to the actual giving of them, after forty years ſpace, the poſſeſſion of <hi>Canaan</hi> of old: ſo God's Peoples coming out of the ſpiritual <hi>Egyptian</hi> Antichriſtian bondage, now approaching, tends to bring all God's <hi>true Iſrael</hi> into the <hi>New-Jeruſalem, that comes down from Heaven,</hi> Rev. 20. and is it not a main drift of the moſt, if not of all the petitions in the Lord's Prayer to this purpoſe? for when hath Gods Name been ſo comparably hallowed in Earth as it is in Heaven, as then it will be, both by Men and Angels, in all he is made known by to his People? When wil his Kingdom come with ſuch power to any ſutable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in Earth as it is, and will be in Heaven, but when the Kingdoms of this World are the Kingdoms of our Lord and of his Chriſt? <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. And likewiſe when at the ſame time, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. God's People ſhall ſo rejoyce when the Lord God Omnipotent reigneth; becauſe, as it followeth in the next verſe, <hi>his Bride hath made her ſelf ready:</hi> And conſequently when will the Will of God be done in Earth, as it is by the bleſſed Angels in Heaven, but when his Subjects are of moſt obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient hearts and loyal ſpirits, as they will be under ſuch a prevalent reigning of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>When may daily Bread, this day [any day] be ſo comfortably and confidently prayed for and expected, as when the particular promiſes of the greateſt confluences of Temporal and Spiritual Bleſſings are to be fulfilled in their proper ſeaſon to their beſt purpoſes? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> When may we with ſuch comfort and confidence pray for forgiveneſs of our Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, this day, [any day] as when our hearts ſhall witneſs with us we leaſt allow our ſins? When ſhall we be ſo aſſured of our own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, as when our ſpirits are moſt free and clear in pardoning others in caſe they offend againſt us? When can we ſo confidently pray to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from the evil one, and evil works, with the conſequents there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of this day [any day] as when Satan ſhall be known to be bound,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102121:9"/>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.3. and many great temptations removed, and a very great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Grace attained, and near Communion with Chriſt enjoyed in this World? Yea, and will not the following enforcements of Prayer ſet down by our Saviour be then moſt clearly applicable, when the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is moſt manifeſtly Gods, and the Power both, to obtain it at his own time and pleaſure? and ſo likewiſe to retain it, appears clearly his; and conſequently all Glory as his due, ſhall be rendred unto him to all eternity. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the Martyrs and Saints to be raiſed at the entrance of Chriſt on this his Kingdom, to have their part in the New <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> I had the like thoughts before to what I find in other Authors, That they ſhould be in a ſtate, ſuch as Chriſt was in after his own Reſurrection, while he was not aſcended to his Father; but when I conſider the many Propheſies of all thoſe great things in the Old Teſtament, ſo confirmed in the New, and ſpecially applyed in the Revelation to the New <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> not only by alluſion, but by application of the Spirit of God and Chriſt himſelf in a ſpecial manner, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.7. as he declared to his Servants the Prophets: And at that time reward is to be given to his Servants the Prophets, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18. and to his Saints, and to them that fear his Name, both great and ſmall, as it follows in the ſame Scripture: And it is of main weight in this point, that when the <hi>Chorus</hi> was ſet about the Throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3. &amp;c. when Saint <hi>John</hi> was to receive the Viſions of that Book, there is a glorious appearance of God deſcribed, and the Rainbow round about the Throne, as doing all to his Church through the Covenant of Grace, through the Blood of Chriſt his only begotten Son; and the ſeven Lamps burning before the Throne, deciphering the ſeven Spirits, or the Holy Ghoſt with his Gifts and Graces, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.4. more clearly in <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. there is a Book in the Hand of him that ſat upon the Throne, which none was found worthy to open but the Lamb, that had been, as it were, ſlain, having ſeven Horns and ſeven Eyes, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. which occaſioned the four living Wights, and twenty four Elders, to ſing a new Song, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards fall down and worſhip; but the top of rejoycing for all that was in the Book, and after all that ſhould be done and ſuffered by, and for, and in Chriſts Church, (which they repreſented in that viſion) it was this, which was the great enforcement of their joy while the World was to continue; <hi>And</hi> (ſay they, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10.) <hi>we ſhall reign upon Earth;</hi> And that Subject, of ſuch their reign there, after all their labours and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Saints, as their time of refreſhment, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19. and Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm or reſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. is largely treated of in ſundry Particulars, in the 19, 20, 21, 22. the four laſt Chapters of the Book of the <hi>Revelations,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:102121:10"/>and that thoſe things therein contained, muſt neceſſarily be underſtood of the ſtate of God's Church upon earth, according to the ſeries and order of the Book in the laſt times, and therefore were never yet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed; take into ſerious conſideration the brief abridgment of Reaſons and Teſtimonies following to that purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is ſaid to come down from God, <hi>chap.</hi> 21.2. and not to aſcend up, or be taken up unto God, as the Church Tryum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant at the laſt day ſhall be, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17. Chriſt will take the Church up to himſelf, <hi>John</hi> 14.3. it ſhall not come down after the laſt Judgment to remain here. 2. The Church is ſaid to be prepared as a Bride adorned for her Husband,
<note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>I conceive the New</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem <hi>that comes down from God, will be a kind of try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant Church, conſiſting of the raiſed Saints, though in the thouſand years, it be not fully glorified, yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly ſanctified and ſaved,</hi> Rev. 20. <hi>knowing in due ſeaſon they ſhall be ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, as</hi> 1 John 3.2, 3.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But all others of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, in the natural life, ſhall walk in the light of that</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, <hi>the Mother of us all,</hi> Gal. 4. Rev. 21.24. <hi>and accordingly the ſeveral Texts relating to either, are to be deſtinguiſhed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> 
               <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. Now the Church Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant, of all the Elect gathered together, is not a Bride prepared, but a Wife in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage fully accompliſhed. 3. Becauſe it is called a Tabernacle, a removing ſtate, and God alſo ſaid to be with men, and to dwell as in a Tabernacle with them; but concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Church Tryumphant in Heaven, the manner of ſpeaking is to ſay <hi>[It is with God.]</hi> 4. Becauſe the Holy Ghoſt ſo ſtrongly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms this renovation of all things, avouching it again and again, <hi>verſ.</hi> 1.5. commanding to write, and affirming the words to be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and true, which needed not in ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally approved believed truth, touching the ſtate of the Church Tryumphant. 5. Becauſe <hi>John</hi> is made to aſcend on high, to ſee this new City below him deſcending out of Heaven from God. 6. Becauſe it is ſaid to be meaſured, and that with the meaſure of a man, <hi>v.</hi> 16, 17. which ſheweth it to be the Church on Earth, which is only meaſurable, and to be meaſured, <hi>c.</hi> 11.1. <hi>Zach.</hi> 1.16. but not the Tryumphant in Heaven. 7. Becauſe here is ſaid, That Nations ſhall walk in the light of it, and Kings of the Earth ſhall bring their glory and honour to it, <hi>verſ.</hi> 23, 24. yea the glory and honour of the Nations too, <hi>v.</hi> 26. But none can bring earthly glory and honour (for of ſuch he ſpeaketh) into Heaven above, to beautifie it withal. 8. This ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not unreaſonable (though ſomething in the Letter carry our thoughts to a ſtate of full perfection, <hi>chap.</hi> 21.4. &amp; 22.3, 4, 5. becauſe the like ſpeeches have been uſed by the Holy Prophets aforetime, to ſet out the graceful and peaceful ſtate of the Church, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.17, 18, 19, 25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 60.18, 20. &amp; 25.8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 60.21. and yet further obſerve, after
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102121:10"/>thoſe high expreſſions, it is ſaid, <hi>chap.</hi> 22.6. Theſe ſayings are faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and true, the Lord God of the Holy Prophets (who had ſpoken of old time) ſent his Angel to ſhew unto his Servant <hi>John</hi> the things [which muſt ſhortly be done] which words, <hi>ſhortly be done,</hi> ſeem al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in this Book to note the ſtate of the Church on earth.</p>
            <p>Now for Teſtimonies in the next place: Some ſuch thing is promiſed to the <hi>Jews,</hi> in the Books of the Prophets, which ſeem not yet to be fulfilled, but deferred till the ſeventh Trumpet be blown, when the Myſtery of God ſhall be finiſhed, as hath been declared to his Servants the Prophets; by which words it is clear, that all things in the Prophets are not accompliſhed, till this Book of the <hi>Revelation</hi> be fulfilled; for the Prophets have formerly ſpoken of this Myſtery to be finiſhed under the ſeventh Trumpet. Now that we may not wonder at the New <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> here ſet forth, look unto the propheſies of old, and mark what by them the Lord did promiſe unto the <hi>Jews</hi> after their captivity. 1. He tells them, They ſhall be brought back again to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and to inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit <hi>Judea, Zach.</hi> 8.7, 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.8, 9. <hi>Iſa</hi> 60.10, 15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 62.10. And this ſhall the Lord do, who ſhall cauſe Righteouſneſs and Praiſe before all Nations, <hi>Iſa</hi> 61.11. 2. He will pour upon them the Spirit of Grace and Supplication, and they ſhall look upon him whom they have pierced, and they ſhall mourn for him, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10, 14. 3. He will make them ſtrong to overcome all their enemies, and they ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> again, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.6. and build the old waſtes; they ſhall raiſe up the former deſolations; and they ſhall repair the waſte Cities, and the deſolations of many Generations, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 58.12. and that by the help of ſtrangers and their Kings, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.10. 4. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo built, whereas it had been forſaken and hated, ſo as no man went thorow it, he will make it an eternal Excellency, and a Joy of many Generations, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.15. For, 1. <hi>Violence ſhall no more be heard in the Land, waſting nor deſtruction within the borders, but her Walls ſhall be called, Salvation, and her Gates, Praiſe,</hi> Iſa. 60.18. <hi>The Sun ſhall be no more her light by day, neither for brightneſs ſhall the Moon give light unto her.</hi> Iſa. 60.19, 20. 2dly. <hi>All the people ſhall be righteous,</hi> Iſa. 60.21. and <hi>no Canaanite there,</hi> Zech. 14.21. 3dly. <hi>Her Officers ſhall be Officers of Peace, and her Exactors, Righteouſneſs,</hi> Iſa. 60.17. 4thly. <hi>Her Watchmen ſhall never be ſilent,</hi> Iſa. 62.6. <hi>neither ſhall her Viſion ever be wanting,</hi> Iſa. 59.21. But the <hi>falſe Prophet,</hi> and <hi>the unclean ſpirit ſhall be cut off,</hi> Zech. 13.2. So as by this glorious and graceful ſtate ſhe ſhall be called by a new name, which the mouth of the Lord ſhall name, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.2. <hi>that is,</hi> Hephziba, <hi>and the Land,</hi> Beulah; <hi>for the Lord would delight in her, and marry her:</hi> or <hi>Jehovah there</hi> ſhall be the name of the City, <hi>Ezek.</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:102121:11"/>48.35. 5thly, Hereupon they ſhall be known among the Gentiles and People, and all that ſee their Seed and Off-ſpring, ſhall acknowledge them the Seed which the Lord hath bleſſed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.9. <hi>An holy People, the Redeemed of the Lord, fought out, and not forſaken,</hi> Iſa. 62.12. 6thly, The Gentiles and their Kings ſhall ſee her Righteouſneſs and Glory, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.12. whereupon they ſhall come to her, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.3. and that with earneſt deſire, and high eſtimation of her, <hi>Zech.</hi> 8.22, 23. and be joyned to the Lord and become his People alſo with her, <hi>Zech.</hi> 2.11. Theſe Nations and Kings ſhall bring to her Sons and Daughters, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.4. and 49.22. Enrich her mightily with abundance, and precious things, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.6, 17. She ſhall eat the Riches of the Gentiles, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.6. and ſuck the Milk of the Gentiles, and the Breſts of Kings, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.16. who ſhall be her Nurſing Fathers, and Queens her Nurſing Mothers, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.23. bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Preſents and Gifts, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.6. and 45.14. they ſhall fall down, and make ſupplication, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.14. they ſhall worſhip with their Faces to the Earth, and lick the duſt of her Feet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.23. <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.16. Strangers ſhall be her Servants, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.5. Yea, ſuch as will not ſerve her, ſhall be deſtroyed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.12. <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.17. <hi>She ſhall be a Crown of Glory in the hand of the Lord, and a Royal Diadem in the hand of her God,</hi> Iſa. 62.3. And this her Excellency ſhall never be changed, her days of mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhall be ended, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.19, 20. Her Joy everlaſting, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.7. For ever ſhall her Land be inhabited, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.21. <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.11. For to the Lord is ſhe married, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.4. who <hi>ſweareth by his right Hand, and the Arm of his Strength, to give her no more over to her Enemies,</hi> Iſa. 62.8. <hi>At that day the Lord ſhall be King over all the Earth; and in that day ſhall there be one Lord, and his Name one,</hi> Zech. 14.9.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee what glorious Promiſes are made to the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> when the Promiſes of the <hi>New Heavens</hi> and the <hi>New Earth</hi> ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, with many other of the like nature: whence it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear how ſtrongly pre-poſſeſſion of prejudice againſt an Opinion, or Doctrine, may carry grave and otherwiſe judicious men away from the Way of Truth; ſometime upon one advantage or other, as by Preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, by Multitudes of wiſe, learned, or even good men (if they try not all things, to hold that which is good, (which was mine own late Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in this particular) or at leaſt want of defecation of appendant Errors, cunningly by Satan affixed on this Truth (as we obſerved in ancient and modern ſeducements, not diſtinguiſhing between the Depravation and Corruption of that Truth, and Truth it ſelf, which in its Original was pure and untainted (as in other caſes many times) when the corrupt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-additions of men have long prevailed to mingle themſelves with anciently untainted Truths, which when men can learn to view with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prejudiced
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102121:11"/>minds, and adhere to with unintereſted Affections, will ſoon appear to them in their native excellency.</p>
            <p>But for the ſaid <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> the more I obſerve many places of Scripture, not onely in the New Teſtament, and <hi>Revelations,</hi> but in the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and even the <hi>Hiſtorical Parts,</hi> the more I am mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereof, from time to time. And beſides, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. &amp; 8. &amp; 96, 98, 99. which one mentions ſpecially, I have taken notice of ſundry others (ſince God hath opened my eyes, as he did <hi>Hagars</hi> of old, to ſee theſe refreſhing Waters of Comfort) as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. &amp; 50. and divers paſſages in others, which ſeemed to tend that way, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. &amp; 148.11, 12, 13, 14. &amp; 149. throughout; and thoſe nine laſt Chapters of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> which the Dutch Bible reckons like <hi>Daniels,</hi> to be Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Old Teſtament, which ſet forth things to be accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the New (though they ſeem not to own the Opinion) yet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times again lay grounds of it. The ſecond and ſeventh of <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeak much of Chriſts Kingdom, and many other places, too largely here to rehearſe. The Spirit of God ſeems to me to have ſpoken ſo largely thereof, and in many ſpecialties likewiſe to theſe purpoſes, and the things themſelves ſeem ſo to approach, as evidently may appear from the Book of the <hi>Revelation</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, (the beſt Expoſitor of the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his own Prophetical Spirit) that it much concerns all Gods Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple diligently to ſearch and examine all ſuch Truths as he hath ſet down there for our now ſeaſonable Inſtruction and Conſolation, being ſunk down near to the very dregs of the Worlds evil Times. And as our Saviour on Earth directed to ſearch the Scriptures for Salvation; ſo now being in Heaven he directs his People to ſearch them in this for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation: And as then he ſaid, <hi>In Moſes, the Prophets, and the Pſalms, it is written of me,</hi> for the former; ſo for this he not onely points out <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Prophets, and the Pſalms in the old Teſtament, but hath like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe taught the Apoſtles, the Evangeliſts, with many other perſons di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely inſpired in the New Teſtament, to give witneſs to theſe things;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide the</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>or peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſts Kingdom</hi> &amp;c.</note> and laſtly by his own wonderful, gracious, divine, though myſtical <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation</hi> to the beloved St. <hi>John,</hi> wherein very much is held out concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his own Kingdom, and the <hi>New Jeruſalem;</hi> and as it was when by the Miniſtry of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, the Doctrine of the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had been more cleared then in former times; yet afterward the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſhews a further Myſtery concerning the ſame, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>We muſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>all be changed, though not all dye;</hi> ſo many things are ſtill Myſteries to us, concerning both the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> and the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, though concerning both, our Saviour in his Revelation hath laſt ſuper-added greater further Diſcoveries in both, than any were before,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:102121:12"/>at leaſt in evidence and clearneſs; Yet how are the Eyes of very many with-held from diſcerning theſe things? and in great part it is like to be ſo to all, ſave to them to whom it is given to know the Myſteries of the Kingdom of God, which he uſes to do, as Chriſt himſelf informeth us, to Babes and Sucklings, when they are hid from the Wiſe and Prudent, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25. and therefore to be humbly and faithfully ſought: And though the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> concerning the Jews general Converſion, had diſcourſed largely in the ninth, tenth, and eleventh Chapters of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> yet ſtill he reckons that Doctrine myſtical, <hi>v.</hi> 25, &amp;c. Let all ſuch therefore as are of truly Chriſtian Spirits, wait upon God, as by other means, ſo by faithful and earneſt Prayer to the true Teacher of his own Myſteries, as may appear requiſite in a matter of ſo great importance, concerning all Gods faithful People, who ſeem to have their peculiar intereſt therein, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21. and 20.4, 5. and 10.18. which is incomparably greater and better for that thouſand years, then all the Crowns, and Scepters, and Kingdoms of the World (not improved in Chriſts ſervice) in the mean time.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>Part of a Letter dated</hi> May 20. 1664. <hi>tending to the opening of the ſeven Seals, Trumpets, and Vials, with the Order of their Times; uſeful for ſuch as are unacquainted with Revelation-Myſteries; with ſome Additions to the like purpoſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe firſt ſix of the ſeven Seals, are the firſt Times after the giving of the <hi>Revelation</hi> to St. <hi>John,</hi> towards the end of the firſt Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or firſt hundred of years after Chriſts coming in the Fleſh; the which ſaid ſix Seals reached to the time wherein <hi>Conſtantine the Great</hi> threw down the Heatheniſh Idolatry in the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, about the year 320. after Chriſt; they are ſet down <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. But out of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Seal proceeded the Seven Trumpets, whereof the ſix firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain all the enſuing time of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, both Chriſtian and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian; and the ſeventh Trumpet will begin at the ruine of Antichriſt,
<note place="margin">Vide, <hi>Paper of</hi> Decemb. 7. 1664. <hi>Where divers Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are given for it.</hi>
               </note> and continue, as ſome conceive, to the laſt day of Judgement, or rather to the beginning of the thouſand years. The firſt four Trumpets (which are reckoned the milder miſeries upon that World of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire) contain ſomewhat above two hundred years after <hi>Conſtantine, Rev.</hi> 8. When the <hi>Goths, Vandals, Hunnes, Almains,</hi> &amp;c. by degrees took away the Emperour, who was he that letted the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102121:12"/>revealing of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> ſpoken of 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. The other three Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, called the <hi>[Vae, vae, vae, Tubae,]</hi> or three Woe-Trumpets, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8. laſt <hi>verſ.</hi> are as follows; The firſt Wo-Trumpet, or fifth Trumpet, is conceived to begin <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 622. according to <hi>Helvicus,</hi> when thoſe Locuſts out of the bottomleſs Pit, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Saracens,</hi> ſubdued and over-ran, one half of the <hi>Eaſtern Roman</hi> Empire, bringing in with them that horrible Impoſture of <hi>Mahometiſm, Rev.</hi> 9. firſt part of the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which continued till about <hi>Anno Domini,</hi> 1300. When the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Wo-Trumpet or ſixth Trumpet is conceived to have begun, when the <hi>Turks,</hi> the other <hi>Mahometan Locuſts</hi> overcame the <hi>Saracens,</hi> and overcame likewiſe the other half of the <hi>Eaſtern Roman Empire, Rev.</hi> 9. latter part of the Chapter, which Trumpet will end with the utter per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the laſt Head of the <hi>Roman</hi> State, <hi>viz.</hi> the ruine of the <hi>Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> being the Feet and Toes of the Image expounded by <hi>Daniel cap.</hi> 2. And for the ſtate of the Church, contemporary with theſe contained in the little Book in the Angels Hand, <hi>Revelations</hi> 10. after a ſhort Chronological Table (as it were) of both Prophecies, <hi>chap.</hi> 11. to <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. and thence to the end of the Chapter, a ſhort Relation of the ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſeventh Trumpet and ſtate of the World, then and thence forward (as after follows.) The firſt Contemporary State of the Church is ſet down, <hi>chap.</hi> 12. containing the <hi>Primative</hi> times, till <hi>Conſtantines,</hi> and the <hi>Dragons</hi> flood of <hi>Arrian Perſecution;</hi> from thoſe times, till the <hi>Womans,</hi> the <hi>True Church</hi> her flight into the Wilderneſs, not long after the Year of our Lord 400. when its probable the Date of the Beaſt began, the falſe <hi>Apoſtatical Church,</hi> when the <hi>Weſtern</hi> laſt Head of the fourth Beaſt, which had received a deadly wound, was again heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſet forth by two Beaſts, <hi>chap.</hi> 13. The firſt having ſeven Heads and ten Horns, deciphering the Politick State; the other with two Horns like a Lamb, and ſpeaking like a Dragon, the <hi>Ecleſiaſtick State</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, whoſe time is forty two months, the ſame with the Lord Chriſts two Witneſſes propheſying in Sackcloth, 1260 dayes of years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. and the Womans, the <hi>True Church,</hi> her abode in the Wilderneſs, for a time, times, and half a time, as <hi>chap.</hi> 12.14. where the Lord's ſaid Witneſſes nouriſh her to the end of the ſaid time, and laſt period of the ſixth Trumpet, under which moſt (if not all) of the ſeven Vials, the ſeven laſt Plagues, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.16. are poured out upon the Beaſt, the <hi>Popiſh</hi> State and Church, to the utter deſtruction thereof, whilſt the 144000 followers of the Lamb ſtand with him upon Mount <hi>Zion, Rev.</hi> 14. harping with their Harps, and ſinging, as it were, a new Song be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Throne, and the four living Wights, and twenty four Elders,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102121:13"/>who are excellently deſcribed, <hi>ver.</hi> 4, 5. till all the Angels had done their Meſſages, and the Son of Man that ſat on the white Cloud, had thruſt in his ſharp Sickle ſeveral times, at the requeſt of the laſt Angels, to reap the Harveſt &amp; Grapes of the Earth fully ripe, to the end of the <hi>chap.</hi> Which Angels ſeem contemporary (if not the ſame) with the ſeven Angels pouring out the ſeven Vials, <hi>chap.</hi> 16. particularly ſet down; And it ſeems probable that the ſixth of thoſe Vials is now pouring out by the <hi>Turkiſh Army,</hi> drying-up the great River <hi>Euphrates</hi> of the <hi>German</hi> Emperors Dominions, and forward towards <hi>Rome,</hi> whereby the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, honour and defence of the Popedom hath been long upheld and conveyed to it. As the great River <hi>Euphrates</hi> was uſeful unto old <hi>Babylon,</hi> until the great Army of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> having turned the waters another way, paſſed thorow the Channel thereof into old <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or, if by ſuch means, with others, as by the converſion of ſome, and plagues and confuſions in others, the <hi>Turks</hi> Dominions, as the great River <hi>Euphrates</hi> ſhall be dryed up in the iſſue, to make way for the <hi>Jews,</hi> the Kings of the Eaſt, to come into <hi>Paleſtine;</hi> yet ſo it will be, the ſixth Vial upon the great River <hi>Euphrates,</hi> and it may not improbably be true of both. The ſeventh Vial will end the Popes Being, and all evil Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, being poured upon the Air, where the Prince of the power of the Air hath ſo long prevalently ruled, which is called <hi>the end of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Wo,</hi> Rev. 11.14. at the end of which the ſeventh Trumpet will ſound, which is called <hi>the Wo-joy Trumpet;</hi> firſt, bringing for the moſt part deſtruction to the Wicked in the World, and likewiſe bringing-in great happineſs to God's faithful People following in the <hi>thouſand years, Rev.</hi> 20. and other things concerning the <hi>New-Jeruſalem,</hi> and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporaries therewith in the two laſt Chapters of the Book of the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations:</hi> Concerning which ſtate of things in the Church (then) I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the not diſtinguiſhing between the ſeventh myſtical Trumpet, and the laſt loud-ſounding Trumpet, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.16. is the occaſion of ſome miſapprehenſions of ſome things to be in the ſaid <hi>thouſand years,</hi> which are alſo an occaſion of ſtumbling to many, as to the matter of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Kingdom of Chriſt upon Earth, whence the great and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den change of all the Faithful is apprehended to be at the beginning of the ſeventh myſtical Trumpet (which I conceive from the Apoſtle's words) will not be until the other loud-ſounding Trumpet, above a thouſand years after, at the laſt Reſurrection and great day of the laſt general Judgment at the end of the World, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. which will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the laſt attempt of the Devil by <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog, Rev.</hi> 20. at the end of the <hi>thouſand years;</hi> at which great ſudden momentany change, in the twinkling of an eye, at the Voice of the Archangel, and ſounding
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:102121:13"/>of the ſaid Trumpet, both all thoſe that were raiſed at the beginning of Chriſt's Reign, or all-along the thouſand years, as learned <hi>Mede</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives; and all the Faithful that are found alive at laſt on Earth, muſt then paſs through that momentany change, and be wrapt up with the Faithful likewiſe, then raiſed to meet Chriſt in the Air in a glorious condition: For, though ſuch as were raiſed before in the beginning of Chriſt's Reign, were before in an excellent ſtate in regard of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, ſuitable to what Chriſt's was in before he aſcended unto the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; yet then it ſeems probable they will be more glorious bodies, than formerly mortal eyes could endure to behold: therefore ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.51. <hi>We ſhall not</hi> (then) <hi>all ſleep, but we ſhall all be changed,</hi> both living and dead. All be changed both living and dead, or raiſed before, namely, all that are faithful; and he repeats it again, the more ſtrongly to aſſertain it, <hi>ver.</hi> 52. latter part of the verſe; <hi>for the Trumpet</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall ſound, and the dead ſhall be raiſed incorruptible, and we ſhall be changed.</hi> It ſeems alſo neceſſary that there be a diſtinct conſideration of the ſtate of ſuch as are of the <hi>New-Jeruſalem</hi> come down from Heaven, which ſeems to be the City, whoſe Maker and Builder is God (as it is ſaid) <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.10. which is again ſaid, <hi>ver.</hi> 16. to be prepared by him for the faithful Fore-fathers that dyed not, having received the Promiſes, <hi>ver.</hi> 13. who without us will not be made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, <hi>ver.</hi> laſt, <hi>having all dyed in Faith;</hi> which is probable to he meant by our Saviour, when he calls it, <hi>the City of the great King,</hi> Mat. 5.35. where his Deputies, the twelve Apoſtles, ſhall ſit on twelve Thrones, judging the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Luke 22.30. on whoſe twelve foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the Wall thereof ſhall be written the names of the twelve Apoſtles of the Lamb, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.14. and ſeems to be the chief manſion-place of the bleſſed, holy, then raiſed Saints, having part in that firſt Reſurrection, wholly then freed from the ſecond death, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.6. up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the Glory of the LORD will then eminently ſhine continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, to the eclipſing of the glory of the Sun and Moon, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.19. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.23. &amp; 22.5. <hi>Very glorious things</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt, in a prophetical rapture) <hi>are ſpoken of thee, O City of God,</hi> Pſal. 87.3. (as is obſervable in that whole <hi>Pſalm.</hi>)</p>
            <p>Again, the (then) happy eſtate of the converted and reduced twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> thoſe two ſticks united into one, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37. together with the converted <hi>Gentiles</hi> in their fulneſs then come in, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. who together with very large endowments of inward ſpiritual Grace, and therewith abundance of temporal proſperity, which the Prophets largely ſpake of, with very much exemption from the evil of ſin and ſuffering, when Satan is bound, the Churches enemies deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102121:14"/>or ſubdued and brought under; which happy eſtate they and their poſterity will ſucceſſively enjoy through all the Generations of the ſaid <hi>thouſand years,</hi> according to the Prophecies or Promiſes, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. <hi>ver.</hi> 1 to 11. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.9. <hi>The Seed which the Lord hath bleſſed,</hi> Ezek. 37.25. <hi>They and their Childrens Children for ever, and my Servant David,</hi> that is, Chriſt the Meſſiah ſhall be their Prince for ever, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59. laſt. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.30, 31. with many texts more; and which were theirs, not in a mortal, (that is) a changeable condition from a natural life, by ſome removal or Tranſlation; as otherwiſe they ſhould have no Seed or Poſterity to enjoy thoſe many Promiſes all the thouſand years, ſo neither ſhould they at laſt be lyable to any evil attempt of Satan, and wicked men, called, <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog;</hi> (though by gracious Promiſe, ſuch as live at that laſt Period of time, are ſecured from the evil even of the attempt likewiſe) Many other things the holy Scripture ſeems to hold forth, in reference to the differing ſtate of the naturally living, and the Saints raiſed at the beginning of the thouſand years; and as for the reſtitution of all things, in reſpect thereof, without Scripture-Warrant, why look we for any more than Gods removing the Curſe? as the inflicting that from the Fall hath been the efficient Cauſe of all that Bondage that hath been ever ſince upon the Creatures, held on by the means of Satan, till then when he ſhall likewiſe be bound. Thus in ſuch a way, if the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction between the laſt myſtical Trumpet, and the laſt ſaid ſounding Trumpet, and the ſtate of the raiſed Saints, and ſuch as then will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in their natural Life, be well obſerved, it may greatly make way for the clearing by degrees (by the help of Gods Word and Spirit) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny excellent Truths reſpecting theſe things, wherein much caution and moderation will ſtill be very uſeful and neceſſary in what things are not clear and evident, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Decemb. 7. 1664. <hi>This Paper ſent upon occaſion of a Book, to be peruſed, not having the right Series or Order of the Book of the</hi> Revelations; <hi>and is added here as a Supplement to the former Letter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS for the peruſed Author, he was manifeſtly a man of great Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, Worth and Piety, as is evident from his grave, judicious, and truly pious Determinations, Diſcourſes, Caſes and Treatiſes of ſeveral Subjects, and many Expoſitions along that large Book of his up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Revelations;</hi> and firſt, more particularly in the moſt things hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by him on the three firſt Chapters to the <hi>ſeven Churches of</hi> Aſia, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:102121:14"/>on the fourth and fifth Chapters, ſetting forth the Glory of God the Creator, and Chriſt the Redeemer; But as for the right ſeries of things, following in that Divine Book, he appears not to have attained the right Key, ſo far as I can, by the guidance of God's Word and Spirit (as I believe) with ſuch other helps, which in ſpecial mercy have hitherto been afforded me, diſcern; and to this purpoſe I ſhall endeavour by his Grace to ſet down ſome brief hints of Differences between him and others, which upon the former accounts I much rather approve of, as namely of judicious <hi>Mede,</hi> and ſome others ſince him, yet living; though haply in ſome things I may differ from all, yet I conceive Light and Darkneſs may ſo thereby the better diſcover themſelves and illuſtrate each other, that whoſo, like the Noble <hi>Bereans,</hi> ſhall ſearch the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures anſwerably, concerning what ſhall be ſet down, may probably find whether all theſe things be ſo: for as no mans eminency ſhould lead us into error, ſo no mans meanneſs ſhould make us neglect or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the Truth he tenders, eſpecially the Divine and Heavenly Truths which God hath ſet forth in his Word, for the true Comfort and Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of his Church; I ſhall briefly, for what is paſt, give onely ſome hints of both, for the moſt part refering to a former Letter to ſuch purpoſes, dated, <hi>May</hi> 20. 1664. which this Paper may be a ſupple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto; but haply ſomewhat more largely of what is to come, as God ſhall direct and enable me, whoſe aſſiſtance, I muſt confeſs to his Glory, I have formerly experimentally found.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, What this Author underſtandeth in the Seals, That the Horſes ſignifie the Church, and the Perſecutions thereof along the Primitive Times, ſeem to me more aptly otherwiſe to denote with Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> and others, the diſpenſations of God in the world, (as in <hi>Zach.</hi> 1.10.) both towards the Church and others with whom they had to do, namely the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> called the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the New Teſtament; and though both the Books of the Seal-Prophecie, and the little Book, <hi>chap.</hi> 10. ſpeak much in ſome ſort of both, yet each chiefly relates to one, as namely the Seal-prophecy for the moſt part to the Empire, and the Book-prophecie for the moſt part to the Church, as after may more by Gods aſſiſtance appear; which is to be obſerved until the Empire and Church become one under Chriſt's Kingdom, in the time, or haply af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the time of the ſeventh Trumpet.</p>
            <p>Therefore after the Lamb Chriſt Jeſus had received the Book at the Hand of him that ſat upon the Throne, <hi>chap.</hi> 5. in the Chapter follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>John</hi> heard the thundring Voice of one of the Beaſts, ſaying, <hi>Come and ſee,</hi> when the Lamb opened the firſt Seal; where he beheld a white Horſe, and he that ſat on him had a Bow, and a Crown was given to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102121:15"/>him, <hi>and he went conquering, and to conquer;</hi> denoting the diſpenſations of God's Grace in the world through Jeſus Chriſt, who received of the Father this Book of <hi>Revelation</hi> of the things concerning the Church and her Enemies, and hath all power to fulfil and execute them according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly here; firſt, ſet forth by the <hi>white-Horſe,</hi> ſo tendering Peace by the Preaching of the Goſpel, which like a Bow, ſhoots out Arrows, (as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.) piercing the Hearts of all ſorts it is ſent unto, and by which Chriſt will be Victorious and Glorious, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and therefore in the ſending abroad of this Goſpel, he goes conquering of all ſorts thereby, and to conquer and ſubdue all ſuch as ſhall oppoſe and perſecute it. This hath been his deſign ever ſince this <hi>white-Horſe</hi> was ſent abroad, guided by that Rider; and this is and will be purſued till he fully have the <hi>Crown of Victory,</hi> when his Enemies ſhall become his Foot-ſtool, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. at the day of the glorious appearing of the great God, and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Titus</hi> 2.13. to begin, at or about, the deſtruction of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.8. when he will come with Clouds, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. and when all Families of the Earth ſhall mourn, ſeeing the Son of man coming in the Clouds with Power and great Glory, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.30. and 26.64. of which deſign the Spirit of God, by the Holy Prophet, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth eminently, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.4. ſaying, Ride on in thy Majeſty becauſe of the VVord of Truth, of Meekneſs and Righteouſneſs, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſubdue unto his Obedience by conquering; <hi>and his right Hand will teach him terrible things,</hi> by conquering and ſubduing his Enemies, and ſuch as withſtand him: And this in all parts of the <hi>Revelation</hi> will be evident; for perſecution will follow the Goſpel, as the Shadow the Subſtance, ſo long as the Seed of the Serpent and the Seed of the VVoman have their aboad together in the world: and therefore, in this Book, in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Seals, God ſeems thereby to manifeſt what diſpenſations be would ſhew towards ſuch perſecuting Enemies in all the following Seals and Trumpets, till that time of eminent victory and conqueſt, begin to be manifeſt unto men in the VVorld at the foreſaid Period, for the great comfort of his Church to be believed from his VVord, and which ſhould be applyed daily for the warning of wicked men if they will be admoniſhed. Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> doth very appoſitely apply the <hi>Red, Black,</hi> and <hi>Pale Horſes,</hi> to ſuch purpoſes in the three following Seals, obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Hiſtories of the Primitive times how they were accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; and (as likewiſe Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> obſerves remarkably) that after the <hi>Roman</hi> Governours had rejected the offer of receiving Chriſt, and that Satan bad engaged them in Perſecutions, above thirty of their Emperours ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively came to untimely deaths; but how ſuch Judgements, of Sword, Famine, Peſtilence, followed one another upon the Empire, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:102121:15"/>all together beſides, as may be obſerved from the firſt, ſecond, and third Seals, but eſpecially from the fourth, as more particularly is ſet down by the aforeſaid Mr. <hi>Mede.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would therefore have obſerved in the fifth Seal the remarkable dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent diſpenſation of God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.</note> when moſt of the ten Perſecutions had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and ſent home ſuch multitudes of believing Chriſtians to bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by their ſufferings; that by the opening of that fifth Seal, is ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to the Church how God was mindful of the Blood of the Martyrs, by the crying of the Souls under the Altar, for revenge; not that they in Happineſs then did complain, or ſo did really cry for Vengeance, but that God looked upon what had been done to them, as an occaſion whereupon he would revenge them, but yet not preſently, but after their Brethren, which ſhould ſoon after ſuffer as they had done, had been likewiſe killed; which ſeemed to have been fulfilled in the Tenth Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution under <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> and Others, which continued ten years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which probably was the ten days Tryal and Tribulation former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpoken of, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10. And accordingly in the ſixth Seal came the great Earthquake, when the Sun became like Sackcloth of Hair, and the Moon like Blood, and the Stars fell, and the Mighty men hid them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the Caves of the Earth, when the wrath of the Lamb was two ways manifeſt: firſt, In dethroning the Dragon, and caſting him down to the Earth, in abandoning the Heatheniſh Idolatry: and ſecondly, By cutting off his Inſtruments, the-then-wicked Rulers of the World, by the means of that Reforming Victorious Conquerour, the Emperour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, when God's hand was ſo heavy upon <hi>Diocleſian, Maximianus, Galerius, Maximinus, Maxentius, Licinius,</hi> and many Governours under their Command, with their Armies; and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on <hi>Ponticius, Culianus, Theotimus,</hi> with many others, as Stories teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie.</p>
            <p>And afterward by taking away by degrees the Seat and Throne of the former Beaſt, who received afterward the deadly wound, upon which the Dragon had ſo prevailed before to perſecute the Saints, as appears in the Trumpets following, which proceeded out of that ſeventh Seal; all of which ſounded their ſeveral Wrath and Judgements againſt it, till it went into utter perdition under every form, both Eaſt and Weſt.</p>
            <p>But before the execution of that Wrath, God would (Chap. 7.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.</note> &amp; 14.) have both his 144000's of the Faithful, ſealed, where thoſe Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets Blaſts ſhould come, who ſhould be ſaved from the ſpiritual miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief of them: and after the ſealing of thoſe 144000, <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. are an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable company of <hi>Palm-Bearers,</hi> of all Nations and Tongues; which the ſaid Author rightly conceives to be the great confluence of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:102121:16"/>Chriſtians, when the Jews, with the fulneſs of the Gentiles, ſhall come in, which will (I doubt not) be in the time of Chriſts powerful Reign, (for this is the courſe obſervable in this Book, (as may hereafter be more manifeſt) that the Spirit of God firſt ſetteth down what Bleſſedneſs ſhall enſue the ſufferings of his People, before thoſe ſufferings come) Now I conceive (with a Learned Author now living) that theſe 144000 ſealed Ones, <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. are another from thoſe 144000, <hi>Cap.</hi> 14. for which he gives divers Reaſons, ſhewing thoſe in <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. were to be preſerved in the Greek Church, in the Eaſtern Empire, and that from the fifth and ſixth, and the part of the ſeventh Wo. Trumpets that might fall there, as to what evil might there fall at the begining of the ſounding thereof; which ſaid ſealed Ones are ſpecially to be preſerved and ſecured at the entrance of the fifth or firſt Wo-Trumpet, by the <hi>Saracen Mahometan</hi> Locuſts, <hi>Cap.</hi> 9.4. and ſo it is to be noted (which I alſo adde) that the blaſts of the firſt four Trumpets, being the milder miſeries on the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, were ſtayed (<hi>Rev.</hi> 8.1, 2.) until much Incenſe was offered by Chriſt, with the Prayers of the Saints, that they might be accepted, where thoſe four Trumpets took effect, namely upon the Weſtern part, from the time the barbarous Nations came in there, for the moſt part till he that letted, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. ſhould be taken away in the Weſt (as he was there firſt) to make room for Antichriſt, to whom the Dragon by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees gave his Seat, and Power, and great Authority: And that the 144000 were to ariſe out of the Greek Church, <hi>viz.</hi> which were ſealed, <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. Some of the ſaid Authors grounds are further, namely, That the Angel that would have the four Winds ſtayed till they were ſealed, is ſaid to ariſe out of the Eaſt, and the evil of the Wo-Trumpets was to fall upon the Eaſt chiefly; and that if thoſe ſealed ones, <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. be not of Chriſtians in the Eaſt Church, in the times of the Wo-Trumpets, there is nothing ſpoken of them in all the Book of <hi>Revelation</hi> remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, which have ſo long been under ſuch ſad tribulation; and their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſaid to <hi>come out of great tribulation,</hi> doth more fitly ſeem to decypher out the Chriſtians of the Greek Church, than any others under thoſe Trumpets: To which I may adde, as being of the ſame Judgement, That they are further deſcribed to have ſpecially waſhed their Robes in the Blood of the Lamb, whom they would not leave for <hi>Mahometan</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtures at the higheſt Price of Fears or Favours, and ſeem to differ from what is ſet down of thoſe 144000, <hi>Cap.</hi> 14. with the Lamb in Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> having their Fathers Name in the Forehead, which ſeems to be in the Weſtern Church, preſerved in the darkneſs of Popery from ſpiritual ruine by Antichriſt, who are called there, <hi>The Followers of the Lamb whereſoever he goeth,</hi> keeping cloſe to him, and not turning into
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:102121:16"/>the Beaſts by-ways and thickets, though he pretended never ſo much to be the Lambs Deputy, and Vicar-General on Earth; and they are ſaid to be <hi>Virgins,</hi> which denotes their avoiding of Antichriſts Idolatry; <hi>and have no guile in their mouths,</hi> to pretend for Chriſt, and follow Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt; with other particulars obſervable, <hi>Cap.</hi> 14. which ſeem to ſet them forth to be the ſealed ones in Antichriſts Dominion, rather than in the Eaſt parts, where <hi>Mahometiſm</hi> prevails, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and therefore the four Angels ſtayed their four Winds while the former 144000, <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. were ſealed, which ſeems to ſignifie they were not to be within the reach of their four firſt Trumpets, that for the moſt part fell upon the Weſtern Empire, till that Seat of the former Beaſt was taken away, and prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould be made for the new Beaſt, the Dragons next Subſtitute, to whom he after gave his Seat, and Power, and great Authority, <hi>Cap.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>For by the firſt Trumper, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8. ſeems to have been weakened the Dominion of the Weſtern Empire, by the incurſion of the barbarous Nations; by the ſecond, the great City or Mountain ſacked or burnt; by the third, the Emperour in the perſon of <hi>Auguſtulus,</hi> the laſt of that Order there, utterly taken away, being plucked out of his Throne; and in the fourth, the light and glory of all that Kingdom formerly, by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away their ancient Senate, by means whereof <hi>Rome</hi> had ſo long ſhined ſo glorious with all her Lights in that Orb before, was wholly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct: but in the fifth, or firſt Wo-Trumpet, (<hi>Rev.</hi> 9. to verſ. 11.) Gods Diſpenſation ſeemed very evident (not in reſpect of Antichriſt, as the fore-mentioned Author conceived) for all the particulars <hi>Chap.</hi> 9. to the 11th verſe, ſeem better to agree to the <hi>Saracens,</hi> than to him. [<hi>Vide</hi> Notes of the Bible on that chapter, and the <hi>Sober Gueſs,</hi> &amp;c. with others.] But againſt the ſpiritual hurt, falling on the one part of the Eaſtern Empire by the Incurſion and Conqueſt made by the <hi>Saracens,</hi> ſome of thoſe before ſealed, <hi>chap.</hi> 7. were preſerved as by means of the two Wings of an Eagle, ſpoken of <hi>chap.</hi> 12. on that part where the <hi>Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens</hi> ſetled; and after on the other part, which the <hi>Turks</hi> took away, beſides what the <hi>Saracens</hi> formerly had; as likewiſe that Woman, <hi>the Church,</hi> had her other Eagles Wing in the Weſt, that Eagle denoting the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire after <hi>Conſtantine</hi> had built <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> in the Eaſt, dividing the Empire into two parts in Eaſt and Weſt; and the Eagle, with her two ſide-wings, being the Enſign thereof: upon which advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, the Woman, the true Church, fled into the Wilderneſs, <hi>chap.</hi> 12. about the end of the ſecond Trumpet, or beginning of the third, (when probably Antichriſt had his riſe, with his ten Kings, or Crowned Horns, ſoon after the beginning of the fourth Century; from which time the ſaid Woman, the Church, hath been fed by her true Paſtors, the two
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:102121:17"/>ſackcloth-Prophets, in her Wilderneſs-condition, which ſhe is ſhortly to come out of. But on the other part, that ſaid Woman, the Church, brought into the Eaſt by the other Eagles wing of the Eaſtern Empire, before into her Wilderneſs-condition, or rather miſerable bondage and great tribulation, being caſt under the ſtroke of <hi>Mahometan</hi> Tyranny by the prevailing of the <hi>Saracens,</hi> at the beginning of the fifth (or firſt Wo) Trumpet, about the year of our Lord, 600. or not long after: who then (I ſay) began to bring her into her great tribulation in the Eaſt on one part, wherein ſhe ſo continued until the ſecond <hi>Wo-Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet</hi> under the <hi>Turk,</hi> about the year of our Lord 1300, by whom the other part of the Eaſtern Empire was ſubdued utterly, and <hi>Mahometiſm</hi> likewiſe prevailed wholly over that formerly famous viſible <hi>Greek</hi>-Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> only the ſaid 144000 of <hi>ſealed ones</hi> have been and are ſtill wonderfully preſerved amongſt them; and even of late, <hi>anno</hi> 1629, or thereabouts, an excellent Confeſſion of Faith, ſent from <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> by <hi>Cyril</hi> late Patriarch there, well approved by judicious men amongſt us, as an evidence of the abiding ſtill of ſuch poor, perſecuted, oppreſſed ſouls in thoſe parts, whoſe great tribulation, ſpoken of <hi>chap.</hi> 7. for about a thouſand years now paſt, and ſtill are like to be under the <hi>Turk</hi> for his day, and week, and month, and year, as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> computes them, his three hundred ninety ſix years, be expired.</p>
            <p>Now when the Spirit of God (as ſeems probable) having ſet forth the Wrath and Judgment upon the very ſeat of the former Beaſt in the ſeaſons of the ſix firſt Trumpets, both Eaſt and Weſt, where in their order they fell; the greateſt part contemporating with Antichriſts Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, both which ſhould be finiſhed at the beginning of the ſeventh Trumpet, whereby the ſame Spirit of God ſeems to lead us by the hand (as it were) to the borders of Chriſt's glorious Kingdom upon Earth, approaching upon the beginning of the ſeventh Angels ſounding, <hi>chap.</hi> 11.
<note place="margin">2d <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, Rev.</hi> 10.</note> He then, in the little book, <hi>chap.</hi> 10. begins again with the affairs of the Church more eſpecially, having ſet forth God's diſpenſations in reſpect of the Empire, both while it was <hi>Draconized,</hi> and after it had been <hi>Chriſtianized.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which little Book when <hi>John</hi> had eaten up, he is told by the mighty Angel of the Covenant, that he muſt propheſie again before Peoples and Nations, and Tongues, and Kings, ſo that they might have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to know theſe Prophecies, had they enquired, as he had ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied: for as it was otherwiſe of them, ſo it was before them; and as he had done it in one reſpect before, (namely) of the Empire, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Church had her being, ſo he ſhould do it again in another re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, namely of the Church, who had her being there: but chiefly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:102121:17"/>under <hi>Antichriſt</hi> in his time, where there was another 144000 followers of the Lamb to ariſe, <hi>chap.</hi> 14.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 11</note> Therefore after the Table of the Times in part of <hi>chap.</hi> 11 to <hi>ver.</hi> 15. wherein we may ſee, <hi>ver.</hi> 1. a deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſtate of the Primitive Times; in <hi>ver.</hi> 2. her ſtate in Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts forty two months; and <hi>ver.</hi> 3. the true Churches ſtate, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the moſt eminent part of it, namely of the Two Witneſſes, her Paſtors, their thouſand two hundred and ſixty dayes of years, who ſhould feed the Woman in her Wilderneſs-condition, and ſtand on Chriſt's part againſt Antichriſt, powerfully and ſucceſsfully, till about the time of finiſhing their Teſtimony, to <hi>ver.</hi> 7. and then what ſhould befal the Beaſt upon his laſt War againſt the finiſhing Witneſſes upon their Reſurrection and Aſcention, after the Beaſt had killed them, to <hi>ver.</hi> 17. where is the ending of the ſecond Wo, and thereupon comes in a ſhort abridgment of the ſeventh Trumpet, containing the great Changes of the Affairs of the World &amp; of the Church, namely, evil to the wicked World, but happy to the true Church: and this excellent Abridgment ſeemed needful, in regard of the great concernment of all ſorts, to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this, as of main uſe to the whole Book. Again, the foreſaid Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor faileth in not diſtinguiſhing between the firſt War the Beaſt makes againſt the Saints and Servants of Chriſt, wherein he kills and prevails, whereupon all the World wonder after the Beaſt; and the ſecond War againſt the Witneſſes, which is diſmal and fatal to himſelf, as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> well obſerves; and hence the ſaid Author reckons the Witneſſes ſlain above an hundred years ago, and ſo paſſeth without taking notice of the laſt finiſhing Witneſſes, as then counting the Beaſts forty two months expired, reckoning the Vials in the ſeventh Trumpet before the ſecond Wo be paſt, or almoſt any thing of the Beaſts ruine begun; which work the Angels that have the Vials are to begin and finiſh, as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> and others judge upon conſiderable grounds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in <hi>chap.</hi> 12.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 12</note> is begun the ſtory of the new Prophecy of the true Church in the Primitive Times, which is there repreſented by a Woman cloathed with the Sun, and having the Moon under her feet, and upon her head a Crown of twelve Stars, whereby was deſcribed the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Primitive Church of Chriſt which ſoon conteſted with the great red Dragon and his Angels, till ſhe by Faith and Prayer obtained the Man-child, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the reforming Emperour, by whoſe means God caſt down the great red Dragon from his heaven upon earth, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his Angels, by which means the Woman had two wings of an Eagle given her, to flie into the Wilderneſs for a time, times, and half a time; but before her flight into that retired hidden condition, the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent caſt out his flood of abominable Hereſies, chiefly againſt the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:102121:18"/>of the <hi>Holy Trinity,</hi> by <hi>Arrius, Eutichus, Macedonius,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to have carried her away thereby, which took up probably al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt an hundred years before her time, times, and half, with <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts</hi> 42 months, took place; all which time from <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> the forementioned Author reckons within the date of the Beaſt, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently he ends it as much too ſoon, as may further appear; and yet for the Earths opening her Mouth, and ſwallowing up of the Dragons flood of Hereſies, what he objects againſt the uſual opinion, to wit, <hi>That it was not the incurſion of the Barbarous Nations, becauſe ſome of them favoured Arrianiſm;</hi> the ſame might likewiſe be objected againſt what he ſayes of the viſible Profeſſing Rulers to be the Earth then oppoſing thoſe Errors in many Councils, though they favoured Superſtition, and ſo might be accounted the Earth; but to that might be anſwered, amongſt them were many in thoſe times good and Orthodox men about the fourth Century, and yet (perhaps) more fitly it might be applyed to the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> and their party, that in thoſe times, to get to themſelves preheminence, did take upon them to end differences in Religion, and became in a ſort famous thereby, getting honour and credit among men thereby, and being to be the Beaſt out of the Earth, acting for earthly ends, the Earth might be ſaid to help the Woman, by withſtanding errors againſt the <hi>Sacred Trinity,</hi> yet promoting ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo might ſwallow up the flood.</p>
            <p>Concerning the two Beaſts in the thirteenth Chapter,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.</note> the ſaid Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor is very excellent, full and clear, above any I have ſeen, if he had timed their riſing rightly, onely he ſeems to confound the number of his Name, <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. with the number of the Beaſt, <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. whereas the firſt denotes evidently the remoteſt ſort of Antichriſts followers, that only may be reckoned or numbred amongſt his party, which were to be in the laſt dayes, as they are deſcribed by the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. when others of the Beaſts party come in the latter times, which forbid Marriage, and command to abſtain from Meats, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3. But the number of the Beaſt, <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. belongs to the Beaſt himſelf, concerning the Expoſition whereof, he giveth a probable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture of his many errors, as the <hi>Sober Gueſs</hi> and others produce many more, which learned and induſtrious men have obſerved, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly oppoſing the Beaſts number, to the 144000, or the meaſure of the Holy City; and I conceive the conſidering, it as <hi>numerus Termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nans,</hi> as <hi>Dan.</hi> 5. may be more conſiderable then many think, as was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in another conſideration, ſetting out what Country man <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt</hi> ſhould be, and what Language he ſhould uſe in his Laws and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, wherein I conceive the wonderful Divine Wiſdom of God is
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:102121:18"/>much to be acknowledged in ſetting down <hi>Myſtery Babylons</hi> name, ſo to exerciſe the ſeveral gifts he hath given to ſeveral men, ſeveral ways, to have their apprehenſions agreeable to truth, and conſiderable in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to this manifold monſtrous Beaſt, wherein they are to be found in one reſpect or other; and ſo the largeſt comprehenſive ſence is like to prove the true ſence, and many of them, to be acknowledged real in ſuch a ſtrange compounded Creature of many, as he is deſcribed <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. And in this Book, <hi>chap.</hi> 14. is conceived by judicious men upon conſiderable grounds, to be contemporary with the two Beaſts,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.</note> ſetting out the oppoſite ſtate of the <hi>true Church,</hi> in the ſame time, not ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive (as this Author takes it) though the Beaſts ruine is therein more fully deſcribed; yet he hath many conſiderable things againſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Antichriſt</hi> in this Chapter; and likewiſe, he is very excellent upon the ſeventeenth and eighteenth, being a like ſubject, to prove the <hi>Pope</hi> to be <hi>Antichriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for the particular Viſion concerning the Vials, <hi>chap.</hi> 15, <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 15, <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.</note> which appears to be a larger <hi>explication</hi> of what was ſpoken of <hi>Antichriſts</hi> downfal and ruine in the latter part of <hi>chap.</hi> 14. As the ſeventeenth was an explication of divers things concerning the <hi>Antichriſtian Church</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> and the eighteenth, a ſpecial Viſion of the terrible, ſuddain, irreſiſtable and curſed deſtruction and deſolation of <hi>Rome</hi> about the ſixth Vial, after which (probably) will ſucceed the converſion of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the <hi>Armageddon</hi>-Battel, of which he hath many profitable notes upon <hi>chap.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>But for the beginning of the ſeventh Trumpet, at the beginning of the pouring out of the ſeven Vials, and placing ſo many of the Vials, after the time wherein the thouſand years (<hi>chap.</hi> 20.) is begun, and making the caſting of Satan into the Lake, after the Battel of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog, chap.</hi> 20. to be the ſeventh Vial, I conceive to be much diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring from the ſence of the Scripture; and for that the ſeven Vials are called the <hi>ſeven laſt Plagues,</hi> which phraſe is the ſame in ſence with the end of the dayes, <hi>Da.</hi> 12. both ſetting forth the period of wicked Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, when the Feet and Toes of the Image he ſaw before, are wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out toward the expiring of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy, and are both ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the Beaſts ruine, and poured out to accompliſh it by degrees, which the laſt Vial finiſheth, and reach no further; and in this ſence learned men underſtand the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Angel of the Covenant, <hi>chap.</hi> 10. <hi>That time ſhould be no longer,</hi> viz. to that wicked Dominion; for thenceforth was to begin a new VVorld, as after <hi>Noahs</hi> Flood, wherein Chriſts Glorious Reign on Earth ſhould take place in an eminent man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, for then the Scene of the World will be viſibly changed, the old
<pb facs="tcp:102121:19"/>being ended, and the new begun, wherein a King ſhall Rule in Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, whoſe Officers ſhall be Peace, and his Exactors Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as the Prophet foretold, &amp;c. then will come in that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that world to come, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. but the Vials are the laſt Plagues, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they at laſt diſpatch and rid <hi>Antichriſt</hi> and all his ſupporters out of the Earth; neither are any ſuch Plagues ſuitable to, or ſeaſonable in the ſtate of things in the ſaid thouſand years, while that happy World remains, and the Kingdoms of the World, become the Kingdoms of our Lord, and of his Chriſt; which this Author applies to the time of <hi>Luther,</hi> which he judges to be the beginning of the Vials (I conceive unwarrantably) when he thinks the Witneſſes were ſlain, <hi>chap.</hi> 11. not diſtinguiſhing of the former and laſt flaying, as we obſerved.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="doctrine">
            <head>
               <hi>Grounds of the Doctrine of Chriſt's Kingdom on Earth, throughout the whole Book of the</hi> Revelations.</head>
            <p>ANd here I ſhall take occaſion to hint what I have all along obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved this Learned and Religious Author to have been defective in; namely, as one not owning the Doctrine of the Glorious King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt to come on Earth in the thouſand years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. That he paſſeth over many things in the Book of <hi>Revelation,</hi> which evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſpect that time, without obſervation; as firſt, in the Epiſtles to the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> wherein thoſe promiſes are ſet down again, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, <hi>c.</hi> 21, 22. concerning the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> many of which are evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently incompetible to any other ſtate of affairs, but of that time, as to have power over the Nations, <hi>chap.</hi> 2.26. to receive the Morning Star, and to eat of that Tree, whoſe Leaves ſhall be for the healing of the Nations, to ſit on a Throne of Chriſt diſtinct from his Fathers Throne, <hi>chap.</hi> 3.21. and to have a Name written of the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> which comes down from Heaven, which are inconſiſtent with the ſtate of the Church Triumphant in Heaven, with divers others, which the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians were ſo well reſolved of in the beſt times, to belong to thoſe that obtained a <hi>better Reſurrection,</hi> as the Spirit of God expreſſeth it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.35. which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſeems to aim at the attaining to, by the fellowſhip of Chriſts Sufferings, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.10, 11. whence the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful are called the <hi>Children of the Reſurrection, Luke</hi> 20.36. Yea obſerve further, they are called by our Saviour, <hi>Such as are accounted worthy to attain that World, and the Reſurrection of the dead:</hi> And to this purpoſe it is ſtoried of the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians,</hi> (ſuch was their Faith in this particular) that out of an holy-ambition (as it were) to have a ſhare
<pb facs="tcp:102121:19"/>amongſt the raiſed Martyrs, they were forward to ſuffer (upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count) for the Name of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But in the next place likewiſe, he paſſeth over what evidently refers to that ſtate, <hi>chap.</hi> 5.10. though he ſpake of what the repreſentative Church are ſaid there to obtain from Chriſt, <hi>to be Kings and Prieſts</hi> (ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually) <hi>unto God:</hi> but he altogether paſſeth over what the holy Ghoſt teacheth them there to praiſe God ſo for the time to come, and which they greatly exult in, and rejoyce in aforehand, for the time to come, as a duty belonging to all Saints in that happy priviledge upon Earth till then, and ſay they <hi>(We ſhall reign upon Earth)</hi> which is joyned to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as another part of their joy, and matter of praiſe, foreſeen by the eye of Faith; as if they had ſaid, For ſo we all, Miniſters and People, ſhall then reign, not only as we did ſpiritually, in our former condition in the world, but as will be ſuitable to that world to come in Chriſt's Kingdom on Earth, <hi>We ſhall reign with him</hi> there <hi>a thouſand years,</hi> as <hi>chap.</hi> 20. is further explained; and to make it clear, it muſt not be taken for Celeſtial Eternal Glory, the place is ſet down where that Reign ſhall be, namely, <hi>on Earth;</hi> and for the time, <hi>future,</hi> noting that it was not their preſent ſpiritual Reign, but they <hi>ſhall ſo reign</hi> there, viz. <hi>on Earth:</hi> What can be ſpoken more clearly? yet by him altogether over-look'd: So uſual it is for prejudice to blind the eyes, even of otherwiſe judicious and good men: though ſome Myſteries of God are diſcovered in their ſeaſons, only to whom, and when, and ſo far only as he is pleaſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal them; as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> recordeth of a Tradition, that the <hi>Apocalyps</hi> ſhould be little underſtood in Antichriſts time, till about the twelfth Century, and ſuitable in ſome things afterwards, in ſuch times as God ſees good, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Again, he takes notice of another innumerable company, cloathed in white, beſides the 144000 ſealed ones, <hi>chap.</hi> 7. which innumerable company of all People, Nations and Languages, having Palms in their hands, he ſeems to underſtand of the flouriſhing ſtate of the Church, when the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhall be called; and he hath many conſiderable Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies to that purpoſe in ſundry places of his Book, but yet he doth not obſerve theſe of both companies are ſet forth to be clothed in white, which is after (as likewiſe before) the clothing of the Inhabitants of the <hi>New-Jeruſalem</hi> that comes down from God, and makes this 144000, <hi>c.</hi> 7. &amp; the other 144000, <hi>c.</hi> 14. the ſame (though they ariſe from ſeveral parts, as we ſhewed, beſides many differences) But that their clothing in white is the badge of the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>-Inhabitants, conſider how the fundamental Promiſes made to Chriſt as Mediator, firſt, to <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> then to <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Sarah,</hi> after to <hi>David,</hi> tend all this way, to
<pb facs="tcp:102121:20"/>advance ſuch a Kingdom of the Mediator <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> upon Earth. Firſt, after that God's everlaſting Goſpel, preached by himſelf when man had forfeited his dominion before-promiſed, <hi>chap.</hi> 1.26. and after could have no right in that or other benefits, but through the Promiſed-Seed; See how this is aſcribed to Chriſt, as his peculiar right belonging to him, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8. And ſee how the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. expounds it ſo, and that with referring it unto that world to come, <hi>ver.</hi> 5, 6, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in which world thoſe <hi>white ones</hi> ſhal have their ſhare, <hi>namely,</hi> in their reigning with Chriſt upon Earth: <hi>Having ſuffered with him, they muſt reign with him</hi> there, as their Captain and King of the <hi>New-Jeruſalem.</hi> See this further in the perſonal Promiſe to <hi>Abraham</hi> firſt, and his Seed; <hi>Not ſeeds, as of many, but unto Thy Seed:</hi> As ſaith the Apoſtle, of one, <hi>viz.</hi> [Chriſt] concerning the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> who yet perſonally poſſeſſed not a foot, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture phraſe is, ſave what he purchaſed for a Burying-place with money, to ſhew his part of that Inheritance; and his faithful poſterities part was to be had after the Reſurrection, and their bones, as <hi>Joſephs,</hi> took and have kept poſſeſſion thereof ever ſince, and will do, till they be raiſed to live upon it again. And ſo after again, the ſaid Promiſe was renewed to <hi>Iſaac,</hi> the type of Chriſt, the Seed of the Woman, in a ſupernatural way, though <hi>Abrahams</hi> likewiſe: And to <hi>Jacob,</hi> that was <hi>Iſrael</hi> for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing with God, having ſeen the Viſion of God before. And therefore the Apoſtle ſaith of them both, They were <hi>Heirs with Abraham of the ſame Promiſe;</hi> to whom it was ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.8. <hi>I will give unto thee, and thy Seed after thee.</hi> The firſt right is his own, which is held only by Faith while he lived, and therefore the actual poſſeſſion yet remains to be enjoyed;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Gen. 26.3. <hi>to Iſaac,</hi> &amp; Gen. 35.3. <hi>the like to Jacob; &amp; to all three</hi> Abraham, Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ac <hi>and</hi> Jacob <hi>together,</hi> Ex. 6.4, 8. <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 30.20.</note> and ſo to <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> who poſſeſſed it no more than <hi>Abraham</hi> in their lives; therefore <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16. with <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.9, 10. they ſo journed in that Land of Promiſe, as ſtrangers, dwelling in tabernacles, with thoſe <hi>Heirs with him of the ſame Promiſe:</hi> and <hi>ver.</hi> 17. ſhews the drift of this Promiſe was to be fulfilled in Chriſt the Promiſed Seed, to poſſeſs that Land, and the reſt, by, and with him. Let theſe Scriptures, and their contexts, be well weighed, with <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.9, 10. for what theſe Promiſes did refer to, is evident, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. namely, the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down from Heaven, whoſe maker and builder is God: and <hi>verſ.</hi> laſt, <hi>he hath provided for them a City:</hi> again, <hi>ver.</hi> 14. <hi>They ſought a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> [not <hi>Meſopotamia</hi>] <hi>but a better Country,</hi> ver. 16. and for which <hi>God is not aſhamed to be called their God, for he hath prepared for them a City:</hi> To this purpoſe he tells <hi>Moſes,</hi> Exod. 3.15. that that ſhould be his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial throughout all Generations, <hi>that he is the God of Abraham, Iſaac, and Jacob:</hi> and upon this Foundation are thoſe many Promiſes in <hi>Moſes</hi> and the following Prophets, that God would reduce their poſterity after
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:102121:20"/>all their diſperſion, to poſſeſs that Land, as in <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. to <hi>ver.</hi> 11. and many other places, too many here to rehearſe; and in Viſion revealed the ſame to <hi>Daniel,</hi> chap. 7. both how and when all ſhould be fulfilled, <hi>when the Kingdom ſhould be given to the Saints of the moſt High:</hi> which is yet more clear and manifeſt by <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. which is the ſame which this Author miſapplyed, <hi>c.</hi> 11.15. <hi>When the Kingdoms of the World are become the Kingdoms of the Lord and of his Chriſt;</hi> that is, in another manner than at the firſt revealing of Antichriſt (as he underſtands it) but gloriouſly, eminently, viſibly, when he hath taken unto himſelf his Great Power, and Reigned, having begun wonderfully to ſubdue his enemies under his feet at the deſtruction of Antichriſt: And this is the drift of our Saviours argument againſt the <hi>Sadduces,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> makes evident on <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. <hi>Mark</hi> 12. that <hi>God was the God of Abraham, Iſaac and Jacob:</hi> therefore they ſhall live again to inherit the Promiſe of the Covenant to poſſeſs the Land of <hi>Canaan:</hi> I do but here briefly hint a few things out of multitudes to the like purpoſe: <hi>Vide</hi> the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>And here from the whole Book of <hi>Revelation,</hi> I may offer this one thing obſervable, namely, That all ſorts of faithful Chriſtians in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Ages and Conditions, have their ſpecial Incouragement held out in ſomething referring to the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> on Earth, though many over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look them, or at leaſt they have not been revealed to them; for men in this caſe are like <hi>Hagar,</hi> till God opened her Eyes in a ſpecial manner, ſhe ſaw not the Well of Water before her; ſo no ſort ſeem to diſcern theſe things, till in ſome remarkable way they be made manifeſt to them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> in the firſt Viſion have each their Promiſes made, in reference to the State of the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> upon Earth.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Repreſentatives of the whole true Church, <hi>viz.</hi> the four Beaſts, and four and twenty Elders, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10. in particular praiſe for, and rejoyce in, their reign upon Earth, to come, which by faith they ſee aforehand; and more eſpecially that ſeems to be the encouragement to the Sufferers under the five firſt Seals; and (as was ſaid) ſeemed ſo to be applied by them.</p>
            <p>Afterwards, the ſealed Ones in the Eaſt, <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. under the wo-Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.4. they have the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> habit upon them, as they ſhall be there happy, and celebrate Gods praiſe; and ſo do the innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable company of all Nations after them, <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. as is evident in the laſt part of that Chapter.</p>
            <p>Again, The four Angels are ſtayed from their blowing the four firſt Trumpets, which fell for the moſt part upon the Weſtern Empire, until
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:102121:21"/>the Angel, <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.3, 4, 5. (probably the Angel of the Covenant) had made interceſſion for the faithful Chriſtians under thoſe four firſt Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, with much Incenſe, with the Prayers of the Saints there abiding, that they might be accepted, who was their ſpiritual Prieſt to intercede for them, and their King to protect them ſpiritually.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Chap.</hi> 11. the two Witneſſes propheſying in Sackcloth 1260 days, have as a general Conſolation to the Church, all that time fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewed to them that they ſhall riſe again, and aſcend into Heaven at the end of the days; and ſoon after have the ſtate of the Kingdom of Chriſt on Earth, foreſhewed unto them in the end of the ſame Chapter.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe the other 144000 <hi>Lamb-Followers</hi> in the Weſtern-Empire, are ſet forth to be with the Lamb in Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> and have this Character of the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> upon them, <hi>That they have his Fathers Name writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten upon their Foreheads,</hi> Chap. 14.1.</p>
            <p>Again, Thoſe that ſhould be Sufferers under Antichriſt, towards his fall, they ſing the Song of <hi>Moſes,</hi> coming out of their Wilderneſs-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and praiſe God for his Judgements upon their Perſecutors, and have the entrance of Chriſts Kingdom upon Earth, ſet before them, for their comfort, <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.4.5. ſo that unto this ſcope drive the Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Sufferers and faithful Chriſtians of all Times, ſince this moſt holy and comfortable Book was given to Chriſts Church; and ſo both thoſe Arms of that red Sea of Blood, running through the Eaſtern and Weſtern Empires in the Churches, meet together at the borders of the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> promiſed to the fore-Fathers and their Seed, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the end of the ſixth Trumpet, and entrance of the ſeventh: And whether it reacheth further then unto that New World, may ſeem que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable; firſt, Becauſe it is one of the Wo-Trumpets, and no ſuch things ſeem ſuitable to the Kingdom of Chriſt upon Earth in the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years: ſecondly, Becauſe the whole continuance of that is ſet forth by another title, for the Comfort of the Church, namely, <hi>Of the Saints reign with Chriſt a thouſand years,</hi> as it were by way of diſtinction from the former ſuffering Times of the Church: thirdly, There is nothing clearly ſaid in the Text that it ſhould continue longer than to bring the <hi>Woes</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Antichriſts Kingdom,</hi> &amp; other Enemies in the World, and ſeems to end with the laſt Plagues, ſo called, becauſe they are the portion of the Churches <hi>Perſecutors</hi> before the thouſand years, and utterly bring them to perdition; and as the ſixth Vial ſeems to end with the <hi>Armageddon-Battel, Chap.</hi> 19. ſo the ſeventh binds and ſhuts up Satan for that thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years, wherein he muſt no more ſeduce the Nations, <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.</p>
            <p>And what this Author ſaith of Satans being caſt into the Lake after the thouſand years, as a Vial, and the laſt Vial of the ſeven, is contrary to
<pb facs="tcp:102121:21"/>the Text, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. at the latter end of the Chapter, where it is ſaid, That when the ſeventh Vial was poured out, the great City was divided into three parts, and then great <hi>Babylon</hi> came in remembrance before God, executed <hi>Chap.</hi> 18. which will be done above a thouſand years before Satans caſting into the lake of fire, where the Beaſt and the falſe Prophet were caſt ſo long before: Beſides, Satans caſting into the lake, ſeems not to be reckoned in the nature of ſuch Vials as gradually brought deſtruction on the Beaſt, and other perſecuting Enemies on Earth, but as his laſt doom at the conſummation of all things, and the diſſolution of the World; which is as much a mercie to ſuch as are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, as a beginning of wo and wrath to Satan, and all damned Men and Devils; but an end onely to the being of inferiour Creatures, which had long before in the thouſand years enjoyed the liberty of the Sons of God, as is ſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.21. Again, The drift of the Trumpets were to blow out Wrath and Judgement upon the Earth, and Graſs, and Trees, <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.4, &amp;c. and ſuch things as were upon the Earth belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to wicked men, till they ſhould be deſtroyed from off the face of it, and there to end; and Satan was then bound in the pit, when there was no work for him to ſeduce ſuch after their deſtruction, who was their Captain and Counſellor before.</p>
            <p>It is likewiſe obſervable what Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> ſaith of the thouſand years wherein the Saints were to reign, That Satan aforehand in the time of Antichriſt ſet them up in a falſe way of reigning, to eclipſe their true reigning that afterward they ſhould have on Earth, and therefore taught Antichriſts Followers to ſet them up ſuperſtitiouſly and idolatrouſly, to worſhip and pray to them, and before their Shrines and Images, making them ſinfully to have a reign with Chriſt on Earth, in ſhew, but really againſt him and his Father: And all that ſaid time of Antichriſt, he hath played the Ape, in ſeeking to pour out the Vials upon Chriſts Kingdom to come, as Chriſt had before declared, that he had ſeven Angels in their times to pour out ſeven Vials to the deſtruction and ruine of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</p>
            <p>The firſt of Satans ſeeming Vials, was, By impoſing <hi>Chiliaſm</hi> upon it, by carnal pleaſures, and typical Worſhip, though upon ſlight, unjuſt and falſe pretences, as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> manifeſts.</p>
            <p>Secondly, By the advantage thereof, he obtained that ſome of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers were ſo prejudiced that they wrote againſt it, though the former for the moſt part were for it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, By ſuch prejudice, and the like, he obtained that good men all along miſplaced the thouſand years by way of anticipation, though differing in the time they began, and expounding them all along the
<pb facs="tcp:102121:22"/>Popes time, onely of a Spiritual Reign.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, By Popiſh falſe Gloſſes and Expoſitions upon all the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> and that part in Particular, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, By ſeducing men of latter times, ſince the Light of Truth began more then of a long time before, to break forth, to ſeek diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly to ſet up Chriſt's Kingdom, which will be Gods own work in his own time, to anticipate the ſame, and that by acting againſt the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine precepts that Chriſt came to eſtabliſh in caſting off due Obedience unto Magiſtrates, and endeavours to ſuppreſs the Miniſtry, thereby to ſcandalize the Doctrine of Chriſt's Kingdom on Earth.</p>
            <p>Sixthly,
<note place="margin">Gr. &amp; Ha.</note> More lately by ſuch as this Author names in the end of his Book, concerning whom he declares much in a few lines, who would make the <hi>Revelation</hi> an Hiſtory of things paſt, rather then a Propheſie of things ſo long to come; ſo that the <hi>Pope</hi> ſhould not be Antichriſt in his forty two months, much leſs Chriſt have a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years Reign on Earth afterwards.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, The ſeventh Vial that Satan hath to pour on Chriſt's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſeems not unfitly to be conceived, to be by diſplacing the Vials, <hi>chap.</hi> 16. from their own time unto Chriſts Reign, whereunto they are not competible, whereof the ſubject matter will be then taken away, or making a groundleſs great Chaſm of above a thouſand years diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, from the ſixth to the ſeventh, when Satan is to be caſt into the fiery Lake, which is a buſineſs of a much differing nature many wayes from all the Vials, as well as in time, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And thus of Satans ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeven Vials on Chriſt's Kingdom; but the glorious appearance of Chriſt will ſhortly aboliſh all appearance of truth in them, and ſo all Satans Vials upon Chriſt's Kingdom will be utterly ended, and yet will not that Kingdom be thereby in the leaſt degree impaired.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Whereas the ſaid learned Author interpreteth the <hi>New Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> to be the <hi>Church Tryumphant,</hi> beſides the many conſiderable reaſons to the contrary, in the Letter of <hi>November</hi> 3. 1664. he might have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved that the Lamb's Wife was ſpoken of before, <hi>chap.</hi> 19.7. by which he there underſtands, the coming in of the <hi>Jews</hi> to the Catholick Church, (I conceive rightly) and that the beloved City, <hi>cap.</hi> 21.2. ſpoken of <hi>chap.</hi> 20. as being before the Battel of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> when the Devil ſtirred up the Hypocrites of thoſe times, which had been long held under by good Government, then to attempt to beſiege that Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved City, though to his and their utter ruine, that ſo they might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that portion of Hypocrites, as the Antichriſtian Scoffers had theirs before, when both ſorts ſhould meet with their Leaders, the <hi>Pope</hi> and the <hi>Devil</hi> in the Lake of fire; and <hi>chap.</hi> 21. being but a further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyphering
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:102121:22"/>of the ſame City, ſhould therefore be expounded according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of that City that was in the thouſand years, it being the obſervable Method of the Holy Ghoſt in that Book, after ſome more obſcure ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of things more generally, afterwards to give more full and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular explications of the ſame, as in the ſeventeenth Chapter, an Explication of <hi>Babylon</hi> and the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> &amp;c. and what was ſaid of the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of <hi>Babylon, chap.</hi> 14. explained by the Vials, <hi>chap.</hi> 15, <hi>&amp;</hi> 16. and further, of the laſt Vials, <hi>chap.</hi> 18, 19, <hi>and part of</hi> 20. and ſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the 19, <hi>&amp;</hi> 20. further explained, <hi>chap.</hi> 21, <hi>&amp;</hi> 22. beſides many things belonging to the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> are incompetible to the ſtate of the <hi>Church Triumphant</hi> in Heaven; ſee the forementioned Letter, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 3. 1663. And for the firſt Reſurrection, it may appear not to be of the Spiritual Reſurrection of the Soul from ſin, both from the drift of the Holy Ghoſt, further, to open the Myſtery of the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had in ſome reſpect ſhewed before, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. And the Doctrine thereof hath been gradually ſet down in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and this, <hi>chap.</hi> 20. giveth light thereunto above all others, both as to the Reſurrection of the Juſt and Wicked, which are oppoſed one to another, as firſt and ſecond, and their diſtinct times ſet out; for as <hi>chap.</hi> 11.18. <hi>When the Kingdoms of the World ſhall be Chriſts, then he gives reward unto his Servants the Prophets, and to his Saints, and to all that fear his Name, both ſmall and great;</hi> ſuch as not only ſuffered for him, (who are ſaid, <hi>chap.</hi> 20. <hi>to be beheaded for him,</hi> &amp;c.) but ſuch as have done his Will on earth, ſhall have ſuch reward from him in earth, as 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. And for ſuch Souls [that is, Perſons, in Scripture language] to live again, what ſence in Reaſon or Religion can fitly be applyed to ſuch ſufferers or others, but ſuch firſt Reſurrection? I know many learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men have tired their parts to find ſhifts to avoid this, but have been more ſollidly and ſubſtantially anſwered, (beſides many others) by Mr. <hi>Mede,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Homes,</hi> in his Anſwer to <hi>Pareus,</hi> Dr. <hi>Predeaux</hi> and others, in one part of the <hi>Dawning of the Day-Star:</hi> read them ſeriouſly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Mede,</hi> conceives that <hi>Reſurrectio Juſtorum,</hi> will be in acting all or moſt of the thouſand years, every one in their own Order; and the <hi>Ancients</hi> conceived there will be <hi>(mora)</hi> delay in reſpect of ſome, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but that the living again of ſuch as were ſo beheaded, to be meant of the Spiritual Reſurrection, is far from the ſcope of the Text, beſides all other conſiderations about it; ſee the Appendix in the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the forenamed Authors, it is, <hi>actum agere,</hi> to ſay much of it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the number of a thouſand years to be taken indefinitely, as it is contrary to the judgment of learned men on both ſides, for many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:102121:23"/>Reaſons; ſo ſomewhat this learned Author mentions himſelf, namely, <hi>That, that, that Thouſand Years,</hi> ſo often ſpoken of in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Saints and Satan, and with all the conſiderable circumſtances, what was done at the beginning of them, with all the continuance, and what ſhould be at the end of them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> might have ſwayed his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment otherwiſe, if he had not been prejudiced againſt the whole Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine thereof, and all that concerns it: for thoſe <hi>Souls</hi> ſaid to be <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed,</hi> cannot fitly be ſaid to live again, but in reſpect of that ſtate, namely, of their bodily living again, wherein they had died before; for as the Spirits of juſt men, they lived ever ſince their departure from their Bodies, ſo that living again, denotes their living bodily, and living in a different manner then they had done before. Now the drift of all theſe things, being for the comfort and edification of all God's People, in this great point of the Reſurrection of the Juſt, and being ſpecially uſeful againſt the evil times, going before the glorious appearing of the great God, and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, when <hi>Antichriſtian Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> ſhould moſt rage in the World; God, in Mercy to his People, is pleaſed now again, to cauſe the Light of theſe Precious Truths to break forth again, more then they have done in many Ages laſt paſt, when that ſaid Glorious Appearance of Chriſt, and beginning of the Day of Judgement, and Joyful Reſurrection following upon it, do in their order neer approach; It is much to be deſired, and earneſtly prayed for, that true Chriſtians would duly weigh and conſider them, being ſo mainly for their Edification and ſound Conſolation, if they will not overlook their own good, or put it off from themſelves, ſince the great goodneſs of Chriſt is therein manifeſt towards them.</p>
            <p>And now for a ſummary of theſe things, I ſhall add, to make up the former <hi>Theſes,</hi> concerning the third Period of Chriſts Kingly Office to be eminently manifeſt therein, where he will work, as I ſaid, by his Spirit of Power and Domination; as he did in the Old Teſtament by his Spirit of Wiſdom and Revelation, and in the New, till his Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Appearance, by his Spirit of Grace and Truth.</p>
            <p>In ſetting down therefore what concerns this third and laſt Period, I ſhall endeavour to expreſs them, either as matter of Faith, or as things that are probable, or laſtly, as things onely conjectural, as the nature of the things may be, and as the clearneſs or obſcurity of the grounds of them may give occaſion.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I believe there is abundant evidence from Scripture, that Chriſt our Saviour will (after the coming of <hi>Elias</hi>) Perſonally, in a glorious manner appear with Clouds, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. or in the Clouds,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:102121:23"/>at or about the great deſtruction of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> which will be as Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſhining from one end of the Heavens to the other; and ſuch ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of his to the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſeems to me probable to be the means of their more general Call and Converſion, when that Nation will be born in a day, (as it were) <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.8. and thereupon will be their mournful contrition promiſed as a Mercy, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10. And then will likewiſe be the Converſion of many Nations of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> not yet called, to bring in their fulneſs, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. And then (Satan being bound from ſeducing the Nations for the thouſand years) the Glorious Kingdom of Chriſt upon earth will be ſet up, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> coming down from God, in the time of the new Heavens and new Earth, wherein Righteouſneſs ſhall dwell, or a King ſhall Rule in Righteouſneſs, (as the Prophet ſpeaketh) The State of that <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> whoſe Maker and Builder is God, will be exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing glorious, a kind of Triumphant State, for the raiſed Saints in their Order, who probably ſhall have their chief Manſions there, till all the deceaſed Juſt ſhall be raiſed, and to the end of the world, the Apoſtles, or other eminent Saints (probably) ſhall be Rulers there by Chriſt's appointment, and all other Governours that are converted to the Truth, and live their Natural Life, ſhall have their directions in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment from them in the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> and all the Teachers in the Church, ſhall, probably, have much inſtructions from them, as they from Chriſt, in whoſe Light they ſhall ſee Light, the Lamb being the Light of the City, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. and that both Spiritual and Viſible, whoſe Tabernacle is then ſaid <hi>to be with men;</hi> when (I conceive) he will be in ſome glorious manner manifeſt unto the raiſed Saints there, whoſe glory they ſhall then behold viſibly, being then made capable to behold it, that none elſe then living can do, except ſo as it was made diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to them by Clouds at his firſt appearing: Yet they likewiſe ſhall all be abundantly filled with his Grace and Wiſdom, and exceedingly rejoyce in all manner of his goodneſs then manifeſt to them, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their then preſent capacity, yet in different degrees and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; and this ſtate will be as intailed to the poſterity of the Faithful, that they and their Seed ſhall be bleſſed, they ſhall live long lives, but how long, I dare not ſay, (but as the dayes of a Tree ſhall their lives be) nor what way of removal, or manner of death, or tranſlation, or change, I know not, but I believe much Mercy and Grace will be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon them and their off-ſpring, ſuitable to ſuch an happy Reign of Chriſt, wherein he ſhall be acknowledged Sovereign by all the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and all authority mannaged under him and for him; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49. <hi>When Kings ſhall eminently be Nurſing-Fathers, and Queens Nurſing-Mothers,</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:102121:24"/>to his Church and People, and the Government upheld in good hands, to promote good, and reſtrain evil, (as it was for the moſt part contrary before) but when Satan being looſed out his Priſon for a little ſpace, ſhall ſeduce the wicked Hypocrites of thoſe times, and draw them from all quarters of the Earth, againſt the Camp of the Saints, and the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved City, upon which attempt God will deſtroy them, caſting the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil into the Lake of Fire, where the Beaſt and falſe Prophet had been long before, and put an utter end to the World by the diſſolution there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, at the conſummation of all things, with the laſt general Reſurrection of the wicked, and general momentany change of the Saints, at the ſound of the laſt Trump, and Voice of an Arch-Angel, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.16. both ſuch as were alive on Earth, and ſuch as were aſleep, to meet Chriſt in the Air (from thenceforth ever to be with the Lord) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon follows the general Judgement.</p>
            <p>Many particulars of theſe natures, it is probable, will in God's time be apparent from Scripture, which we can now but gueſs at, which God to his Faithful Servants may diſcover, concerning which we ſhall only ſay with the Antients, <hi>Elias cum venerit nodos ſolvet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for the main ſubſtance of all this Doctrine, what is it, but the explaining of ſuch Articles of Chriſtian Faith, as we all profeſs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve concerning theſe things in the true Scripture ſence, wherein Chriſt hath taken ſpecial order to have his Faithful People rightly inſtructed, as in many particulars forenamed? Firſt, When we Profeſs, <hi>We believe that Chriſt ſhall come from the Right Hand of the Father, to Judge quick and dead;</hi> He will ſo come at his glorious appearing to deſtroy <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi> to begin his Judgement, and make his Foes his <hi>Footſtool, Pſ.</hi> 110. until which he was to ſit at his Fathers Right Hand in Heaven; then the Scripture ſaith, <hi>He judges quick and dead,</hi> as <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18. and elſewhere (though afterwards likewiſe) in this ſence, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10. the Angel (Chriſt) Swears, <hi>Time ſhould be no more,</hi> which ſeems to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20. ſo the end of the dayes, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. for the ſame Period, <hi>vide,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and that it is the day of Judgement at leaſt begun, Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> largely and excellently ſhews, in his fourth Letter to Mr. <hi>Hain,</hi> and to Dr. <hi>Twiſſe, &amp;c.</hi> both from Scripture and Antiquity, and that he will wonderfully Reign with his raiſed Saints a thouſand years; Why ſhould it be doubted, when his Word ſpeaks ſo much and evidently for it? though the Truth hath, by Satans ſlights, been clouded for a time, wherein there ſeems to be, as it were, an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing of the great laſt Aſſizes, and calling together the Aſſeſſors thereof, the Saints; doth not the great Law-giver and Judge, inform his Church of theſe things? and he muſt needs be the beſt Expoſitor of his own Will, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="commentary">
            <pb facs="tcp:102121:24"/>
            <head>Sept. 27. 1664. <hi>A Paper ſent upon occaſion of ſome diſcourſe concerning the great and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Appearance of Chriſt about the time of finiſhing his Kingdom of Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and of ſetting up his Kingdom of Viſible Power on Earth, the firſt being the Kingdom of the Stone, cut out of the Mountain,</hi> Dan. 2. <hi>Then the Kingdom of this Stone becomes a Mountain</hi> [<hi>as Mr.</hi> Mede <hi>fitly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſheth their times by</hi> Regnum Lapidis &amp; Regnum Montis.]</head>
            <p>AS for the perſonal appearance of Chriſt at the deſtruction of Antichriſt, and the general calling of the Jews, when that Nation ſhall be born in a day, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.8. many Texts of Scripture ſeem to me fully to evidence it; as firſt, that great Promiſe, That <hi>they ſhall look upon him whom they have pierced, and mourn,</hi> with ſuch a penitent Contrition promiſed to them in mercy, <hi>Zac.</hi> 12.10. compared with <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. with <hi>Even ſo Amen,</hi> as a great mercy in its time to be accompliſhed. And from St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Sermon to the Jews, when he tells them, That <hi>the times of refreſhing from the preſence of the Lord, at the reſtitution of all things, ſhall come, when God will ſend Jeſus, whom the Heavens muſt contain till then,</hi> Act. 3.19, 20, 21. which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> calls, <hi>Chriſts apearing at his Kingdom,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.1. and in <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. after the little Horn (the Pope) ſpoken of before, verſe <hi>9. the Ancient of Days did ſit,</hi> and in verſe 21. <hi>the little Horn prevailed until the Ancient of Days came,</hi> verſe 22. which is further explained, verſ. 26, 27. And <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. after the coming of the Son of man was deſcribed by the Lightning from one part of the Heaven to the other, and after the trouble then to be upon the Earth, <hi>verſ.</hi> 29. it is ſaid, <hi>Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ſhall appear the ſign of the Son of man,</hi> which is probably conceived to be Chriſt himſelf, as a ſign then to the whole World; and the time ſeems decypher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, verſe 24. <hi>that that Generation ſhall not paſs,</hi> namely, in that the Nation of the Jews was to remain diſtinguiſhed from all other People, [for they have been, and will be preſerved moſtly unmixed with others, until the appearing of Chriſt] and as, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Antichriſt is to be deſtroyed at the appearance of his coming:</hi> So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.39. <hi>Ye ſhall not ſee me till ye ſhall ſay, Bleſſed is he that cometh in the Name of the Lord;</hi> implying that then they ſhall ſee him: And in that Parable up-upon the occaſion of the time of the appearing of the Kingdom of God, <hi>verſe</hi> 11. having before, <hi>Chap.</hi> 17. compared the days of the Son of man to the days of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> which latter, of <hi>Lot,</hi> ſeems to reſemble the next appearing of Chriſt, and the former, namely, of <hi>Noah,</hi> his laſt coming to Judgement, thoſe two days of the Son of man: Now as <hi>Lot</hi> and his Family were ſent out of <hi>Sodom</hi> firſt, before <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> were deſtroyed in that particular deſtruction, ſo the Faithful ſhall firſt come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and ſpiritual <hi>Sodom,</hi> before it be deſtroyed in that partial deſtruction, though like to be very great and terrible: And as <hi>Noah</hi> and his in the general Deluge were carried by the Ark above the deſtruction of the old World by Water; ſo in the general conflagration of the World at Chriſts laſt coming, all the Faithful at their great &amp; general change, ſhall be caught up to Chriſt their ſafe Ark, in the Air, above the deſtruction of the Wicked by fire, at the Worlds laſt deſtruction; and, as the Rabbins ſpeak from the Prophet, <hi>Their ſtrength ſhall then be renewed like the Eagles,</hi> and be there with Chriſt in ſafety, as neither lyable nor capable any more of any ſuch miſery: (I ſay) then in the 11th Chapter, he ſpeaks of ſuch a coming, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. when he will reckon with ſuch as would nor have him reign over them, and with the unprofitable Servant at his coming, <hi>v.</hi> 23.
<pb facs="tcp:102121:25"/>and will have thoſe his Enemies then brought and ſlain before him, <hi>verſ.</hi> 27. when he ſhall receive his Kingdom, and return, as <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. and this Parable was particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly ſpoken by our Saviour to reſolve the miſtake of ſuch as thought the Kingdom of the Meſſiah ſhould then immediately appear, <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. And many of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers expreſſions import as much, which I ſhall not now inſiſt upon: But for how long, and in what manner he may be perſonally preſent, ſo as <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. he is ſaid to <hi>come with Clouds</hi> (haply) to unvail the brightneſs of his Glory, which otherwiſe mortal Eyes could not endure, I dare not ſay: for as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, he <hi>dwelleth in the light which no man can approach unto;</hi> (otherwiſe) <hi>As no man hath ſeen him, ſo no man can ſee him,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.16. and whether after ſome time of his appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſonally, that expreſſion of the <hi>Tabernacle of God its being with men,</hi> as <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.3. imports ſome wonderful Glory and Grace upon the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> as upon the Tabernacle of his Grace of old; or the Glory of God ſhining upon it, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.1. whoſe Sun and Light ſetteth not day nor night, <hi>verſ.</hi> 19, 20. by ſome bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Glory and Grace ſhining upon her continually, making glad the City of God, when the Lamb ſhall be her Light, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.23. or their beholding of him, as <hi>Stephen</hi> did miraculouſly at his death, ſitting at Gods right Hand; or in what manner the Ark of Gods Teſtament ſhall then be ſeen, when the Temple of God is opened in Heaven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.19. with many expreſſions to like purpoſe; or how long that <hi>Reſurrectio Juſtorum</hi> ſhall be in finiſhing which Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> in one of his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſeems to conceive may be a great part of the thouſand years, and according to their order (as the Apoſtles phraſe is) firſt of the Martyrs, and moſt eminent Saints, and ſo of the reſt ſucceſſively; concerning which, and the like, as I am in the dark, ſo I muſt be ſilent: God in his own time will reveal what he knows beſt for his People; in the mean time there is matter enough of Comfort and Rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing in reſpect of both Quick and Dead, in the good and bleſſed Condition of his Church, in the ſaid thouſand years upon Earth, to all ſuch as ſo wait upon Chriſt here, as the true Followers of the LAMB, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. that they may be in a capacity of the Happineſs reſerved for either ſort in thoſe times; for which the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures give plentiful Evidence, if Men will not hide their Eyes from the Light thereof.</p>
            <p>Thus, Chriſtian Friend, I have as in a Mirrour briefly (being led by the Hand of Divine Providence, and aſſiſted by his Grace and Spirit, according to his Word) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to ſet before thee theſe Materials of the <hi>New Jeruſalem-Doctrine,</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that hence thou mayeſt (with me) have gladneſs put into thy Heart, above what men have when their Corn, and Wine, and Oyl encreaſeth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with this Prayer for Thee and my Self, <hi>That the Knowledge and Faith of theſe things may be ſanctified dayly more and more unto us, and may more and more engage our Hearts unto the LORD, to whom all the ſervice of our whole Spirits, Souls and Bodies, is ever due:</hi> and in the faithful endeavour therein, our labour will never be in vain:</p>
            <p>Many other things I ſhould here have added to like purpoſes, but am now for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to defer them, till God may afford ſome further engaging Opportunity: In the mean time, let us render unto Him the Glory of all we are, or have, or do, or expect, which ever of Right will belong unto His Divine Majeſty.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>To Glory's GOD all Glory's due for aye:</l>
               <l>To Him alone, This Due, let all His pay.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The End.</trailer>
            <trailer>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>In the Title Page, for <hi>Aurorum</hi> read <hi>Auroram;</hi> pag. 26. l. 7. r. <hi>they,</hi> p. 25. l 4. r. <hi>caſt up,</hi> p. 31. l 36 r <hi>ſaid wings,</hi> and l. 40. r. <hi>fifth Century,</hi> p. 32. l. 21. add <hi>to be expired.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:102121:25"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
